<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: markdown | Wern Ancheta]]></title>
  <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/categories/markdown/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-03T18:35:53+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://wern-ancheta.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Wern Ancheta]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning Markdown]]></title>
    <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2012/08/13/learning-markdown/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-13T18:00:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2012/08/13/learning-markdown</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Octopress uses markdown for its source files so its required for me to learn
markdown if I want to blog using Octopress.</p>

<p>In this article I&rsquo;m going to walk you through the syntax of Markdown(this will also serve as my guide later on when I start to forget things like an old man, though not all old man forgets things).
But before we get started let me discourage you a bit. Markdown is not as complete as html. Things like table doesn&rsquo;t exist in markdown(though there&rsquo;s probably no need for it if you&rsquo;re doing a tech blog).</p>

<h4>Headers</h4>

<p>Headers are indicated by the number of pound signs that you use before the actual header text:</p>

<p>```</p>

<h1>This is equivalent to H1 in HTML</h1>

<h2>This is H2 since there are 2 pound signs before the text</h2>

<h3>You get the point now(this is H3)</h3>

<p>```</p>

<h4>Paragraph</h4>

<p>You write paragraphs in markdown just like you write them when writing a letter. Just separate paragraphs with whitespaces.</p>

<p>```
This is a paragraph</p>

<p>This is another paragraph
```</p>

<h4>Links</h4>

<p>Links are also easy to write just place the descriptive text inside brackets and the link itself inside parenthesis.</p>

<p><code>
[Google.com](http://google.com/)
</code></p>

<p>If the link is the same with the descriptive text you can just do it this way:</p>

<p><code>
&lt;http://google.com/&gt;
</code></p>

<h4>Images</h4>

<p>Images are also written like links. The one inside the brackets is the alt text. And the one inside the parenthesis is the link to the image itself.</p>

<p><code>
![some_image](http://localhost/someimage.png)
</code></p>

<h4>Lists</h4>

<p>How you write ordered lists is just like how you write them in real world:</p>

<p><code>
 1. Im item number 1
 2. Im item number 2
 3. Don't forget the spaces between the dot(.) and the item text
</code></p>

<p>And this is how you write unordered lists:</p>

<p>```
 * You can use a plus sign(+), minus sign(&ndash;), or an asterisk(*)
 * It still renders as bulleted list
  * But the bullet style changes as the list gets deeper</p>

<pre><code> * And you can do that by using whitespaces(1, 3, 4) 
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<h4>Conclusion</h4>

<p>There are more things that you can do with markdown so checkout the resources below to learn more.</p>

<h3>Resources</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Daring Fireball &ndash;  Markdown</a></li>
<li><a href="http://warpedvisions.org/projects/markdown-cheat-sheet/">Markdown Cheat Sheet</a></li>
<li><a href="http://joncom.be/experiments/markdown-editor/edit/">Markdown Editor</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
