<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: newsletters | Wern Ancheta]]></title>
  <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/categories/newsletters/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-14T14:14:53+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Wern Ancheta]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Newsletters I subscribe to]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2014/09/07/newsletters-i-subscribe-to/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-07T10:10:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2014/09/07/newsletters-i-subscribe-to</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Following last weeks post on <a href="/blog/2014/08/31/podcasts-i-listen-to">Podcasts I listen to</a>. This time I&rsquo;ll talk about some of the newsletters I subscribe to.</p>

<h3>Ruby Weekly</h3>

<p>Ruby Weekly is an email round-up of Ruby news and articles. This newsletter is mainly about Ruby but you can also find some interesting stuff here even if you&rsquo;re not a Ruby developer. Links to articles about command line tools, databases and version control are also included in every issue.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Friday</p>

<p><a href="http://rubyweekly.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>JavaScript Weekly</h3>

<p>JavaScript Weekly is an email round-up of interesting JavaScript news and articles. It also has a jobs section in which you can find jobs exclusively for JavaScript developers or engineers.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Friday</p>

<p><a href="http://javascriptweekly.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>Webtools Weekly</h3>

<p>Web Tools Weekly is a front-end development and web design newsletter with a focus on tools. Each issue features a brief tip or tutorial, followed by a weekly round-up of various apps, scripts, plugins, and other resources to help front-end developers solve problems and be more productive.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Saturday</p>

<p><a href="http://webtoolsweekly.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>Gamedev.js Weekly</h3>

<p>Gamedev.js Weekly is a newsletter all about HTML5 game development. I&rsquo;m not really a game developer myself so reading articles from this newsletter is just for me to have an idea how games for the browser are being developed.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Saturday</p>

<p><a href="http://gamedevjsweekly.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>StackExchange Programmers Newsletter</h3>

<p>A curated list of interesting programming questions from the programmers.stackexchange website.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Saturday</p>

<p><a href="http://programmers.stackexchange.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>DB Weekly</h3>

<p>A weekly round-up of database technology news and articles covering new developments, SQL, NoSQL, document databases, graph databases, and more.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Friday</p>

<p><a href="http://dbweekly.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>Versioning</h3>

<p>A daily newsletter by Sitepoint. If you are tired of keeping yourself updated via your twitter feed, hacker news, and a bunch of other sources then Versioning is for you. As they curate a bunch of links that web developers might find useful.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.sitepoint.com/versioning/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>Hacker Newsletter</h3>

<p>If you can&rsquo;t keep up with Hacker News, Hacker Newsletter is the way to go. Kale Davis curates only the most interesting stuff that you might find on Hacker News.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Friday</p>

<p><a href="http://www.hackernewsletter.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>Responsive Design Weekly</h3>

<p>A free, once–weekly round-up of responsive design articles, tools, tips, tutorials and inspirational links.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Friday</p>

<p><a href="http://responsivedesignweekly.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>Node Weekly</h3>

<p>Node Weekly is a free, once–weekly e-mail round-up of Node.js news and articles. Its still from the same guy (Peter Cooper) who brought us the awesome JavaScript Weekly Newsletter. But this is primarily focused on Node.js.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Friday</p>

<p><a href="A%20free,%20once%E2%80%93weekly%20e-mail%20round-up%20of%20Node.js%20news%20and%20articles">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>WPMail.me</h3>

<p>WPMail.me is a free WordPress Newsletter, once a week, with a round-up of WordPress news and articles.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Friday</p>

<p><a href="http://wpmail.me/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>PyCoder&rsquo;s Weekly</h3>

<p>A free weekly e-mail newsletter, on Fridays, for those interested in python development and various topics around python.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Saturday</p>

<p><a href="http://pycoders.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>Python Weekly</h3>

<p>If PyCoder&rsquo;s Weekly isn&rsquo;t enough, Python Weekly has got you covered. Its a free weekly e-mail newsletter, for those interested in python development and various topics around python.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Friday</p>

<p><a href="http://www.pythonweekly.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>PHP Weekly</h3>

<p>As the name suggests, PHP Weekly is a newsletter featuring the best articles, tutorials, talks, news, jobs, and tools about PHP. Based on my experience so far, every issue is a fat one. And when I say fat it means that there&rsquo;s bunch of stuff in there for you to consume. You couldn&rsquo;t ask for more from this newsletter. Its the best thing there is if you want to keep yourself updated about PHP stuff.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Thursday</p>

<p><a href="http://www.phpweekly.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>Postgres Weekly</h3>

<p>Postgres Weekly is a free, once–weekly e-mail round-up of PostgreSQL news and articles.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Wednesday</p>

<p><a href="http://postgresweekly.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>Web Design Update</h3>

<p>Web Design Update is a plain text email digest dedicated to disseminating news and information about web design and development with emphasis on elements of user experience, accessibility, web standards and more</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Wednesday</p>

<p><a href="http://lists.d.umn.edu/mailman/listinfo/webdev">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>ng-newsletter</h3>

<p>Ng-newsletter is a weekly newsletter of the best AngularJS content on the web.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Wednesday</p>

<p><a href="http://www.ng-newsletter.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>Ember Weekly</h3>

<p>Ember Weekly is a newsletter dedicated to bring you the latest Ember.js news, tips and libraries.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Monday</p>

<p><a href="http://emberweekly.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>HTML5 Weekly</h3>

<p>HTML5 Weekly is a newsletter that features HTML5 and Web Platform technology roundup, CSS 3, Canvas, WebSockets, WebGL, Native Client, and more. Basically all things HTML5 and related technologies.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Wednesday</p>

<p><a href="http://html5weekly.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>Perl Weekly</h3>

<p>Perl Weekly features hand-picked news and articles about Perl.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Monday</p>

<p><a href="http://perlweekly.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>DevOps Weekly</h3>

<p>Devops Weekly curates the best and latest articles all about DevOps. If you&rsquo;re not familiar with DevOps, its basically a short term for Development and Operations. Its mainly focused on IT operations, tooling and collaboration.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Monday</p>

<p><a href="http://www.devopsweekly.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>UX Newsletter</h3>

<p>Another newsletter from Stackexchange which features the most interesting questions about User Experience in the past week.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Monday</p>

<p><a href="http://ux.stackexchange.com/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>Web Developer Reading List</h3>

<p>An all in one newsletter for web developers. It contains news on both front-end and back-end stuff.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Friday</p>

<p><a href="http://wdrl.info/">Visit Site</a></p>

<h3>CSS Weekly</h3>

<p>A weekly e-mail roundup of css articles, tutorials, experiments and tools curated by Zoran Jambor. There&rsquo;s not much in every issue but the quality makes up for it.</p>

<p>Schedule: Every Tuesday</p>

<p><a href="http://css-weekly.com/">Visit Site</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
