<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: job | Wern Ancheta]]></title>
  <link href="http://anchetaWern.github.io/blog/categories/job/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://anchetaWern.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-06T11:32:46+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://anchetaWern.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Wern Ancheta]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Things I learned on my second job]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetaWern.github.io/blog/2013/02/10/things-i-learned-on-my-second-job/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-10T15:58:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetaWern.github.io/blog/2013/02/10/things-i-learned-on-my-second-job</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this blog post I&rsquo;m going to share some of the things that I learned on my second job.</p>

<!--More-->


<h3>Apache Solr</h3>

<p>Apache Solr is a search platform that&rsquo;s available for different languages like Ruby, PHP, and Java.
Solr&rsquo;s main feature is that its very fast. It returns either XML or JSON.
There&rsquo;s a library available for PHP which is the one that I used. It&rsquo;s called <a href="http://code.google.com/p/solr-php-client/">solr php client</a></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a sample query for accessing data that&rsquo;s available in the Solr server:</p>

<p><code>
http://localhost/solr/select/?q=id:%search&amp;wt=json&amp;rows=%max_results
</code></p>

<p>As you can see its just like accessing data from an API like the one provided by Twitter or Facebook.
You can use Solr via server-side or client side.</p>

<p>If you want to access its data via the server-side you can use the <code>file_get_contents()</code> php function or <code>curl</code>.
If you want to access its data via the client-side you can use the <code>$.ajax</code> jQuery function.
But if the Solr server is located on a different server you can use the <code>jsonp</code> data type.</p>

<h3>Wordpress Plugin Development</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also learned about Wordpress Plugin Development and the Wordpress platform as a whole.
<a href="http://codex.wordpress.org/">Codex</a>, the main documentation site for Wordpress has some really good guides and reference for the different functions that are available from Wordpress.</p>

<p>When developing Wordpress plugins you will almost always have to hang out in these 2 pages:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://codex.wordpress.org/Plugin_API/Filter_Reference">Filter Reference</a></li>
<li><a href="http://codex.wordpress.org/Plugin_API/Action_Reference">Action Reference</a></li>
</ul>


<p>In Wordpress filters are used for processing the things that are already outputted by Wordpress like the content of a blog post or the title of your blog. Filters are used to modify, add, or hide content.
This is very useful for filtering out things like profanity in blog posts.</p>

<p>Actions in Wordpress are events that happen inside wordpress like publishing a new blog post or creating a new page or activating a plugin. You can hook into these actions to execute a specific function that will do something when these events happen.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s also a built-in class for accessing the Wordpress database which is the <a href="http://codex.wordpress.org/Class_Reference/wpdb">WPDB</a> which you will most likely use if the plugin that you&rsquo;re trying to build needs to persist data in a database (E.g for storing settings that your plugin will use).</p>

<h3>API&rsquo;s</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also learned how to use API&rsquo;s like the <a href="http://www.flickr.com/services/api/">Flickr API</a>, <a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AWSECommerceService/latest/DG/CHAP_ApiReference.html">Amazon Product Advertising API</a>, <a href="http://developer.ebay.com/common/api/">Ebay API</a>, and <a href="http://wiki.freebase.com/wiki/Freebase_API">Freebase API</a>.
Since this will be used by the Wordpress plugin that I&rsquo;m developing.</p>

<h4>Ebay API</h4>

<p>The Ebay API was particularly easy to use since they have a very good documentation.
And by good documentation I mean things are easy to find.
The documentation also has everything that a developer who is just getting started with using the API wants to know.</p>

<h4>Amazon Product Advertising API</h4>

<p>The documentation for Amazon Product Advertising API was the exact opposite of the Ebay API documentation.
Things were hard to find and you can&rsquo;t even find examples on how to use the API on languages like PHP.
Thankfully I found this blog post on <a href="http://www.codediesel.com/php/accessing-amazon-product-advertising-api-in-php/">how to access the product advertising API in PHP</a> which made life easier.</p>

<h4>Freebase API</h4>

<p>The Freebase API was also easy to use because the API itself is relatively simple.
The Freebase API was divided into different services like Search, Image, Text, Topic, etc.
Each of those returns different sets of data in JSON format.
Freebase is already owned by Google so you can basically acquire an API key or access key from the Google API console.</p>

<h4>Flickr API</h4>

<p>The Flickr API is also comparable to the Amazon Product Advertising API when it comes to difficulty.
Though the documentation is very good it lacks some examples on how to access the API using different languages.
But the <a href="http://phpflickr.com/">PHPFlickr</a> library made my life easier.
All I had to do was to specify the App ID and App secret for my Flickr App which can be created at the <a href="http://www.flickr.com/services/apps/create/">App Garden</a> and then I can just call the methods which I need.</p>

<h4>Coinbase API</h4>

<p>Coinbase is sort of like Paypal but for Bitcoins. Bitcoin is a digital currency that can be used to pay for goods and services. Coinbase is a service that allows you to buy, use and accept bitcoins for payments.
The Coinbase API is used to interact with the Coinbase service. You can do a bunch of stuff with it like listing out all the changes on your Coinbase account, get the current balance in BTC (Bitcoin Currency), generate buttons to be used for paying for services and goods, retrieve contacts, orders, transactions any many more.
The things that you can do with the Coinbase API are all listed in the <a href="https://coinbase.com/api/doc">API Documentation</a>.</p>

<p>Authenticating API calls can be done using either the API Key or <a href="http://oauth.net/2/">OAuth2</a>.</p>

<p>YOu can also use the <a href="https://github.com/coinbase/coinbase-php">Coinbase PHP</a> library to easily communicate with the Coinbase service.</p>

<h3>Drupal Custom Module Development</h3>

<p>I also learned a bit about custom module development in Drupal. I can say that its tough, you can&rsquo;t just hack your way out to produce a working solution. But the good thing is that most of the problems is more or less already solved by an existing module. All you have to do is install it and figure out how to integrate your own custom module with it.</p>

<h3>Responsive Web Design</h3>

<p>I also learned a bit of responsive web design. <a href="http://learn.shayhowe.com/advanced-html-css/">The Advanced HTML &amp; CSS guide</a> by Shay Howe really helped me a lot in learning responsive web design.</p>

<h3>Shopify App and Theme Development</h3>

<p>Recently I also learned about Shopify app and theme development. Shopify is an online e-commerce platform, you can use Shopify to create online stores to sell goods and services. Its sort of like Wordpress, Magento, Drupal, Joomla or other CMS (Content Management System) but only focused on e-commerce and you cannot actually download the platform and host it in a server somewhere. Shopify takes care of everything, that includes installing, upgrading and maintaining the software. But you have the freedom to choose your own domain.</p>

<p>Shopify really did a great job with their documentation, you can get up and running in a short time. Here are some links to get you started with Shopify development:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="Shopify%20API">http://docs.shopify.com/api</a></li>
<li><a href="Shopify%20Themes">http://docs.shopify.com/themes</a></li>
</ul>


<p>That&rsquo;s all for this blog post. I will continue to update this blog post once I learn more things from my second job.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Things I learned on my first job]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetaWern.github.io/blog/2012/08/23/things-i-learned-from-my-first-job/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-23T17:03:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetaWern.github.io/blog/2012/08/23/things-i-learned-from-my-first-job</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4>Non-technical</h4>

<ul>
<li>Nothing is ever written on stone, the clients mind changes all the time. It&rsquo;s always wise to prepare for
changes that the client might want to push to the live website.</li>
<li>As developers we should always keep ourselves updated of the latest technology, software development methodology, or just
things that happens in our industry. I&rsquo;ve written a post about <a href="http://anchetawern.github.com/blog/2012/08/16/how-to-stay-updated-as-a-developer/">how we can stay updated as developers</a>.</li>
<li>Not everything that the client wants is possible(or possible to accomplish in a short period of time) sometimes
you just have to admit that you can&rsquo;t do something rather than saying that you can do it and then the deadline
comes and you really have nothing to show.</li>
<li>Be honest to yourself. If you can&rsquo;t do it, you can&rsquo;t do it(but you probably can given enough time).</li>
<li>Sometimes you just have to do things outside of the ticking clock. What I mean by this is that even
if you&rsquo;re being paid for a job at an hourly rate sometimes you just have to do things that are part of your job
even if the clock is not ticking since its part of having pride in the job that you do and its a proof that you really love doing your job.
Some of the things that I do when not directly working with my project is learning the technologies that I might
probably use in the project. Just playing around with it will do. And by the time that you have to apply it to the project that you&rsquo;re
working on it will be as easy as pie.</li>
<li>Sometimes the payment gets delayed because of a bad weather or changes in the schedule of payment, or a problem in the company.
These are normal and you really have to wait. But if the delay gets longer than 1 week, then it really is a problem and you probably need
to set your own rules when it comes to delayed payments. Some people make it a point that when payment is delayed by
a specific period of time they will charge twice the amount that is supposed to be paid, if it gets delayed another day they multiply it by 2 again.
And we really can&rsquo;t blame them(especially the rockstars, superstars and ninjas) since they do their work well, they deliver(even before deadlines),
and they really take pride in the work that they do.</li>
<li>If you can&rsquo;t work on a specific day do your best to tell your boss in advanced atleast 1 day before the day that you will be out
tell your boss that you&rsquo;re gonna be out. But of course you won&rsquo;t be able to do this all the time. What if you suddenly got sick? or a
rushed family outing, or your house has been flooded. In those cases you need to have the mobile number of your boss so you can always
inform the situation even if you&rsquo;re not in front of the computer.</li>
<li>There are different ways in which companies try to track your time. Some use a time-tracking software like time doctor which also takes
screenshots of your desktop automatically. Some use a spreadsheet where you have to log what you&rsquo;ve done for that particular day</li>
</ul>


<h4>Technical</h4>

<p>There&rsquo;s actually too many to mention in detail so here&rsquo;s a few:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Openinviter</strong> &ndash; This is a PHP Class that is basically used for connecting to email service providers such as Gmail, Yahoo Mail and Hotmail</li>
<li><strong>Hotmail API</strong> &ndash; I actually gave up half the way while trying to retrieve contacts from hotmail since they&rsquo;re hashing the emails. But I might
go back to working on this once required by the client.</li>
<li><strong>Yahoo Query Language</strong> &ndash; just like SQL but you&rsquo;re just querying Yahoo&rsquo;s database. This is specifically useful for retrieving information
for your yahoo mail contacts.</li>
<li><strong>Facebook JavaScript SDK</strong> &ndash; I&rsquo;ve learned <a href="https://developers.facebook.com/docs/authentication/permissions/">how to set permissions</a> using the scope property in which you set to a collection of strings separated by
a comma(just a comma no other characters like whitespaces). I&rsquo;ve also learned how to access basic user information and friends information.
You can also specify extended permissions on the scope which allows you to do more awesome things using the Facebook API.</li>
<li><strong>Facebook meta tags</strong> &ndash; most of the time the Facebook documentation doesn&rsquo;t make any sense that&rsquo;s why articles like that of
David Walsh on <a href="http://davidwalsh.name/facebook-meta-tags">Facebook Open Graph Meta Tags</a> is always useful.</li>
<li><strong>CPanel</strong> &ndash; I also learned how to use Cpanel specifically the parts where you create database, managing the database. I also experimented
on the ssh stuff since I want to install Git on the server but that&rsquo;s just a failed attempt coz I don&rsquo;t have admin privileges.
I haven&rsquo;t really gotten much around with it because I might break something.</li>
<li><strong>FTP</strong> &ndash; I also learned FTP specifically the Filezilla. FTP is basically a way to connect to a remote server given that you have
the correct login information. I learned how to set file and folder permissions. There are 3 permission groups namely the <code>owner</code> , <code>group</code> and <code>public</code>
and there are also specific number for file permissions <code>4</code> for read, <code>2</code> for write and <code>1</code> for execute, <code>0</code> if there&rsquo;s no
permission to do anything on that file or folder. So if you want to enable just the read and write and not execute the permission is 6(just add the numbers together)
if the user can do anything on that file then the permission is <code>7</code></li>
<li><strong>Smileys on Skype</strong> &ndash; ok this last one is probably(definitely) irrelevant but I actually learned how to use smileys/emoticons on skype. I&rsquo;ve been
using skype for almost a year and I haven&rsquo;t realized that the happy face beside the SMS checkbox is where you can select emoticons to use on the
conversation.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
