<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: jekyll | Wern Ancheta]]></title>
  <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/categories/jekyll/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-14T13:45:55+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Wern Ancheta]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction to Contact plugin for Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2014/08/02/introduction-to-contact-plugin-for-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-02T21:01:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2014/08/02/introduction-to-contact-plugin-for-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this blog post I&rsquo;ll be introducing the <a href="https://github.com/anchetaWern/jekyll-contact">Contact plugin for Octopress</a>.
This plugin allows you to create contact forms with ease. Its using the <a href="http://pooleapp.com/">pooleapp.com</a> for saving the data for the forms that are submitted.</p>

<h3>Create a Pooleapp account</h3>

<p>First lets go through pooleapp. Poole is a free, hosted data store for static sites. It allows you to post data into it and then later on you can retrieve the data using a simple API.</p>

<p>You don&rsquo;t have to register to start using pooleapp but its recommended so that you can keep track of the forms that you create. Another bonus feature is that when someones submits a data to your contact form, pooleapp will immediately notify you via email.</p>

<p>Once you&rsquo;ve registered an account, you can now create a new form. Just give your form a unique name and click on the &lsquo;create form&rsquo; button. Once created, pooleapp will ask you for the email in which you want the notifications to be sent to.</p>

<h3>Installing the plugin</h3>

<p>Octopress doesn&rsquo;t really have a plugin system so we&rsquo;ll have to do things manually. First thing that you need to do is to add the <code>contact.rb</code> file into the <code>octopress/plugins</code> directory.</p>

<p>So that we can show a success message once the visitor submits his data through the contact form, we also need to add the <code>contact.js</code> file inside the <code>source/javascripts</code> directory. Basically what it does is to check for the existence of the <code>form</code> query parameter. If it exists then it makes the success message visible.</p>

<p>For the styling, add the <code>_contact.scss</code> file inside the <code>sass/partials</code> directory. Then in your <code>sass/_partials.scss</code> file, import the css for the contact form by adding the following on the last line:</p>

<p><code>
@import "partials/contact";
</code></p>

<p>Lastly, under the <code>source/_includes/custom</code> directory, add a script tag that points out to the <code>contact.js</code> file on the last line:</p>

<p>```</p>

<script src="/javascripts/contact.js"></script>


<p>```</p>

<h3>Using the plugin</h3>

<p>To use the plugin in any of your pages, simply use the <code>contact</code> liquid tag then supply your pooleapp API key as the first argument, and the redirect URL for when the form is submitted:</p>

<p>
<code>
{% contact YOUR_POOLE_APP_API_KEY http://YOURSITE.COM/PAGE?form=ok#alert-box %}
</code>
</p>

<h3>Demo</h3>

<p>You can try out the demo on the <a href="http://wern-ancheta.com/aboutme">about me page of this blog</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction to Portfolio plugin for Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2013/08/18/introduction-to-portfolio-plugin-for-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-18T20:19:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2013/08/18/introduction-to-portfolio-plugin-for-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this article I&rsquo;m going to introduce Portfolio, an Octopress plugin that I created for easily creating portfolio pages based on the images on your filesystem.</p>

<p>The portfolio plugin is a liquid tag type of plugin which means that it gives you the ability to use the tag to generate a specific content. In this case the portfolio plugin allows you to generate image tags based on the images in a directory that you specify.</p>

<h3>How to Install</h3>

<p>You can install the portfolio plugin by simply copying the <code>portfolio.rb</code> file into the <code>plugins</code> directory of your Octopress installation.</p>

<h3>How to Setup</h3>

<p>You can setup the plugin by opening up the <code>_config.yml</code> file and specify the root directories in which the plugin will look for the files that it will be using.</p>

<p><code>
portfolio_root: /portfolio
portfolio_img_root: /images/pages/portfolio
portfolio_path: /web_files/blog/octopress/source/images/pages/portfolio
portfolio_url: images/posts/pages/portfolio
</code></p>

<p>The <code>portfolio_root</code> is the name of the directory where your portfolio is saved.
The <code>portfolio_img_root</code> is where the images for your portfolio is saved.
The <code>portfolio_path</code> is the actual path in your filesystem where your portfolio is saved.
And the <code>portfolio_url</code> is the address where you can access your portfolio from the browser.</p>

<p>The plugin doesn&rsquo;t come with a default styling so you have to add them on your own. You can simply hook up to the markup that has been provided,
that is the <code>gallery-item</code> class.
In the example above I gave it a default <code>width</code> and <code>height</code>.
The <code>overflow</code> is set to hidden so that the image that it contains won&rsquo;t overflow.
The <code>margin</code> is <code>10px</code> all around. Lastly, its floated to the left so it would align nicely.
You can add this on the <code>sass/base/_layout.scss</code> file or anywhere you feel would be appropriate.</p>

<p>```css</p>

<h1>content .gallery-item {</h1>

<pre><code>float: left;
width: 390px;
height: 150px;
overflow: hidden;
margin: 10px;
border: 1px solid lightgray;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Next create a directory where the details of your projects will reside. The ideal location would be in the <code>octopress/source</code> directory. This should be the same as the value of the <code>portfolio_path</code> that you have included in your <code>_config.yml</code> file earlier. Each of your project will have its own directory, so if you have a project named <code>echo</code> then you have to create the following directory: <code>octopress/source/portfolio/echo</code>.</p>

<p>Also create the directory where the images for each of your project will reside. Following the path that we specified earlier we should have the following directory for project <code>echo</code>:</p>

<p><code>
octopress/source/images/pages/portfolio/echo
</code></p>

<p>The <code>echo</code> directory is where you will save your images. If you intend to use lightbox or any other alternative you can simply put <code>small-</code> as a prefix to the name of your image files. The images with this prefix will automatically be used as the initial image and the one without it will be larger image. So if you have an image file named <code>index.png</code> you also need to have <code>small-index.png</code> file. Of course this should also be resized. Having the browser do the resizing for you by setting the width and height of the image using css is not a good idea.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also recommended that you run your images through an image optimizer before you actually add them to the directory as Octopress won&rsquo;t optimize it automatically. This is to ensure that your project page will load faster.</p>

<h3>How to Use</h3>

<p>You can use the plugin by using the <code>portfolio</code> liquid tag followed by a single space then the name of your project. Just put on underscores if you need spaces. Also there shouldn&rsquo;t be any special characters. For our imaginary <code>echo</code> project:</p>

<p>
<code>
{% portfolio echo %}
</code>
</p>

<h3>Resources</h3>

<p><a href="http://jekyllrb.com/docs/plugins/">Jekyll Plugins</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
