<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: updates | Wern Ancheta]]></title>
  <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/categories/updates/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-15T07:41:43+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://wern-ancheta.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Wern Ancheta]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Developers New Years Resolution]]></title>
    <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2016/01/04/a-developers-new-years-resolution/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-04T20:11:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2016/01/04/a-developers-new-years-resolution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s 2016. A brand-new year is upon us. And this is the time of the year when people usually set goals for the new year. While most other folks have new year&rsquo;s resolution for their real life, In this article I&rsquo;ll be sharing some of my new year&rsquo;s resolution as a developer.</p>

<h3>Generate Passive Income</h3>

<p>The idea of generating a passive income has really enticed me in the past but it&rsquo;s only this year that I&rsquo;ve thought about it seriously. For developers one way of generating passive income is through marketplaces like Themeforest and CodeCanyon. All you have to do is build something useful and you can sell it on the platforms that I&rsquo;ve just mentioned. I&rsquo;ve already created an account on CodeCanyon, set it up and read their terms. All that&rsquo;s left for me to do is to build something and submit it for review so that people can find it.</p>

<h3>Continue What I&rsquo;ve Started</h3>

<p>I have a bunch of projects on Github. Some might not already work. Some lacking in documentation. This year I&rsquo;ll continue every project that I started. Or at least mention that I won&rsquo;t already be doing active development for projects that I&rsquo;m no longer interested in pursuing.</p>

<p>I have also a blog series that I started back in 2014 which I called: <a href="http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2014/02/09/a-whirlwind-tour-of-web-developer-tools/">A Whirlwind Tour of Web Developer Tools</a>, I&rsquo;m planning to start that up again this year.</p>

<h3>Be More Picky</h3>

<p>I read a lot. In fact I&rsquo;ve created <a href="http://updatedapp.github.io/">a website</a> that curates all the news from sources that I want. Usually these are from the developer newsletters, twitter users, and websites that I follow.
But I&rsquo;m still subscribed to the newsletters which I have used as the news item source. So it still gets the better of my time when I receive a new issue. My plan is to unsubscribe to all of those newsletters and just stick to using the website myself. This is so that I don&rsquo;t accidentally engage to some content. Or click on a link and not actually reading what&rsquo;s in there. With the new setup I can actually just visit the website if I really want to read something and not when I receive a new issue of a newsletter.</p>

<p>The second step after unsubscribing to all newsletters is to actually pick only what I really want to read. If its a tool that I can use in the future, then I save it on my delicious account. If its an article which I want to go back to in the future then I save it on Pocket.</p>

<p>The third step is to actually read what&rsquo;s really important or at least something that I really want to read. Of course this can&rsquo;t be determined by merely looking at the title so the article has to be scanned first and then determine if it&rsquo;s really relevant.</p>

<p>Of course this goes with all the other content that I&rsquo;m consuming and creating. So movies, anime shows, personal projects, blog posts should go through a tight consideration before I actually engage on it.</p>

<h3>Be More Healthy</h3>

<p>Developers have a sedentary lifestyle by nature. Just sitting on a chair coding all day. That&rsquo;s no good so here are the steps that I&rsquo;m planning to implement to be more healthy.</p>

<ul>
<li>Indoor exercise in the morning. Intense outdoor exercise in the weekends.</li>
<li>Use the standing desk at least one hour in the morning and one hour in the afternoon.</li>
<li>Eat less rice.</li>
<li>Eat more fruits and vegetables. There should be at least one meal per day where I eat a decent amount of those.</li>
<li>Get more sunlight.</li>
<li>Sleep more.</li>
<li>Be more concious about my posture.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Engage More in the Community</h3>

<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ll start by creating videos <a href="http://youtube.com/WernAncheta">on Youtube</a> showing a specific technology, tool or methodology regarding web development. I&rsquo;ve already started it the previous year by uploading some of my flipped classroom videos that I&rsquo;ve used in my class in the school where I teach.</li>
<li>Comment on other developers blog posts, or talk to them on twitter.</li>
<li>Answer questions on Stackoverflow.</li>
<li>Attend local developer meetups.</li>
<li>Contribute to open-source projects.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Use Tools</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been pretty much avoiding the use of tools in my day to day job as a developer. I still use plain css instead of Less, Sass, Stylus or {insert your css preprocessor of choice here}. I still don&rsquo;t use Grunt, Gulp, Brocolli, Carrots, Eggplant, {insert your build tool of choice here} for every project (note: there&rsquo;s no carrots or eggplant yet but someone might create it after this). I&rsquo;ve been avoiding the use of tools because I just want to get started with a project fast. Installing a bunch of tools and setting them up before I can start coding is a pain. The only tools that I currently use are the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Composer</li>
<li>Bower</li>
<li>npm</li>
</ul>


<p>Simply because you can&rsquo;t install anything without those.</p>

<p>This year I&rsquo;ll start by learning how to use Yeoman so I can easily setup all the things that I need for a project. And then learn how to use a css preprocessor, Gulp to process the project assets, JSLint to check the quality of my JavaScript code. And then in the back-end use PHPUnit for unit-testing.
And lastly use a continuous integration server such as Jenkins to automatically run unit tests so that I immediately know if a specific code is still working or not.</p>

<h3>Build More Cool Shit</h3>

<p>Pardon the language but developers are <a href="https://twitter.com/gitlost">commonly foul-mouthed</a> right? Anyway, what I mean by build more cool shit is to create stuff that I can be proud of. I&rsquo;d also like to build IOT (Internet of Things) projects. And with the birth of the RaspberryPi zero it just got more easy. Though I&rsquo;m yet to order one because the stock is always zero. I should have ordered one when I first heard about it. Now people are ordering it non-stop. Who wouldn&rsquo;t right? RaspberryPi zero is only five fucking dollars.</p>

<h3>Learn a New Language, Framework, Tool, Methodology</h3>

<ul>
<li>Language: Python &ndash; If I am to build stuff with RaspberryPi I need to learn to code in Python. I also want to leap from the hybrid app bandwagon and go full native so I&rsquo;ll have to learn (or rather re-learn) Java. This is simply because apps built with Hybrid App Framework such as Cordova performs poorly on my old android phone. Maybe I just need a new phone but I&rsquo;ll go ahead and blame it to programming.</li>
<li>Framework: Symfony &ndash; I&rsquo;m basically a Laravel guy so for a change I pick Symfony.</li>
<li>Tools: CI Server, PHPUnit, Gulp, Sass, ReactJS</li>
<li>Methodology: I&rsquo;m still not sure. But I&rsquo;ll probably try to learn some of the most popular design patterns in JavaScript and PHP.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Get Better at What I Do</h3>

<p>No matter how good you are at something there&rsquo;s always room for improvement, there&rsquo;s always another way for doing things twice as easy or efficient. So the plan for 2016 is to look for ways to improve my current development workflow. Like I said earlier I&rsquo;m a Laravel guy so I&rsquo;ll start by examining my current Laravel workflow and see what I can improve.</p>

<h3>Invade Other Fields</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been really interested in UX because I know it will be helpful for me as an all-around developer. When I say all-around it means I&rsquo;m the one doing the server setup up to deployment and anything between those two. I&rsquo;m pretty much a one-man band in all the projects that I&rsquo;ve built so far. No devops, no designer, no nothing.</p>

<p>Another field that I&rsquo;d like to look into is SEO. Who wouldn&rsquo;t want to have their website more findable?</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it! How about you? What&rsquo;s your plan for 2016?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Year-end Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2015/12/29/2015-year-end-review/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-29T12:14:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2015/12/29/2015-year-end-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A year is coming to an end again. And with lots of free time during the holidays I figured it would be nice to reflect on the previous year. So in this post I&rsquo;ll be sharing some of the things that happened in 2015.</p>

<h3>Career</h3>

<p>As you might already know I&rsquo;m a developer. So I develop websites and apps for a living. I mainly do home-based work since I graduated from college. Mainly because of its convenience and for personal reasons. You get to work from home and earn money how cool is that? But recently its no longer that fun. Payments get delayed. And projects are no longer that interesting. I basically stopped doing it around October of this year. Good thing I got hired as an author for Tutsplus' Mobile channel. And I still write for Sitepoint. So I currently write articles for those two awesome websites full-time.</p>

<p>Around July this year I got a message from my college instructor asking if I want to teach. I said yes. And so from August until December I taught at the college where I graduated from. It&rsquo;s only part-time during the afternoon so I still got to write full-time. From my 4 months of experience I can say that I really enjoyed teaching. Being able to share what you know and helping your students get better, it&rsquo;s one of the most rewarding feelings ever.</p>

<p>Since teaching in college requires someone to have a master&rsquo;s degree in their field. I had to take up Master&rsquo;s in Information Technology. Good thing the school is only walking distance from my home so it&rsquo;s very accessible. And classes are only on saturdays. So I&rsquo;m still able to do what I like doing the most: coding.</p>

<h4>Projects</h4>

<p>This career section wouldn&rsquo;t be complete without me talking about projects. If you look at my <a href="https://github.com/anchetaWern">Github profile</a> there are lots of new additions to the list of repos this year. This is mainly because I always write tutorials on making apps with different web technologies. Sitepoint and Tutsplus requires those apps to be in a Github repo. That&rsquo;s why my Github has got a bunch of those apps. Another reason for the repo population growth is free time. I already mentioned that I currently write full-time. But I don&rsquo;t necessarily have a boss. So I still got to choose whether to write for a certain day or work with another thing. Some days I choose to work on my personal projects. The common theme for my personal projects is usually to solve some problems that I&rsquo;m having. Mainly automation stuff so I don&rsquo;t have to do a lot of things manually. My part-time teaching job has particularly lots of problems that needs solving. This includes: <a href="/blog/2015/09/27/introduction-to-absentist/">attendance tracking</a>, managing of files submitted by students, <a href="/blog/2015/10/25/introduction-to-shotgun/">checking of student activities</a>, <a href="/blog/2015/11/03/introduction-to-grade-viewer/">showing grades to the students</a>.</p>

<h3>Health</h3>

<p>Developers are mainly sedentary animals. That&rsquo;s why there&rsquo;s a need to make an effort to thwart the effects of sitting in front of the computer all day long. As for me what I did was to use a standing desk. And jog first thing in the morning.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I've been up to lately]]></title>
    <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2014/07/06/what-ive-been-up-to-lately/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-06T17:52:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2014/07/06/what-ive-been-up-to-lately</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You might have noticed that I no longer publish new blog posts as frequently as I have
before. That is because I&rsquo;ve been busy with other stuff lately. It all started when I joined Islick Media last March. My job at Islick Media is pretty much the same as a regular job where you work 8 hours a day, 5 days a week. Nothing out of the ordinary.</p>

<p>Then I got an unexpected project from someone who read my blog post on Amazon Product Advertising API. I was hesitant at first because I&rsquo;m already happy with my job and I am happy with my salary. After some pondering I thought that extra income would be nice so I tried to give it a shot and I emailed the person back, making it clear that I currently have a full time job and that I would only be able to do this project on my free time. The person then replied back saying that its ok. Then the rest is history. I got the project last April and until now the project is still ongoing so most of my free time goes into that.</p>

<p>Going back to the month of February I also tried emailing Sitepoint, a company dedicated to making awesome articles on web development. It was pretty much a cold email saying that I wanted to write for them. That I&rsquo;ve been writing articles about web development for a while but I&rsquo;ve only been doing it on my blog and that I wanted to try and make money doing it.
I&rsquo;ve waited but I didn&rsquo;t get a reply after a week so I thought they&rsquo;re not interested. But then after exactly a month, the managing editor of Sitepoint PHP Channel emailed me back with an apology for not getting back to me sooner. But the important part is that I got an ok. And man! that was the most awesome feeling ever! Sitepoint is one of the most popular websites which publishes resources (books, articles, courses) on web development. The fact that I get to write for them is really just awesome.</p>

<p>Lastly, I&rsquo;m also occupied with my personal project hoping that it would turn into a nice source of passive income. I can&rsquo;t tell something about the project yet but once I get it out there I&rsquo;ll be publishing a blog post about it so stay tuned for that.</p>

<p>And that&rsquo;s pretty much what I&rsquo;ve been up to lately. I don&rsquo;t think I&rsquo;ll be able to write anything lengthy on blog soon. But I&rsquo;ll try publishing some short tutorials so I still have fresh content in my blog even if I&rsquo;m busy. But basically the series on the Whirlwind tour on Web Developer Tools isn&rsquo;t going to continue soon. I&rsquo;d like to provide as much information as I could on each part of the series. But I don&rsquo;t think I have time to write lengthy posts so I&rsquo;m going to temporarily stop the series.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it for this blog post. At times like this I really wish the <a href="http://dragonball.wikia.com/wiki/Hyperbolic_Time_Chamber">Hyperbolic Time Chamber</a> was for real so I don&rsquo;t need to prioritize things and just do everything I want to do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
