<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: updates | Wern Ancheta]]></title>
  <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/categories/updates/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-06T18:06:48+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Wern Ancheta]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I've been up to lately]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2014/07/06/what-ive-been-up-to-lately/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-06T17:52:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2014/07/06/what-ive-been-up-to-lately</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You might have noticed that I no longer publish new blog posts as frequently as I have
before. That is because I&rsquo;ve been busy with other stuff lately. It all started when I joined Islick Media last March. My job at Islick Media is pretty much the same as a regular job where you work 8 hours a day, 5 days a week. Nothing out of the ordinary.</p>

<p>Then I got an unexpected project from someone who read my blog post on Amazon Product Advertising API. I was hesitant at first because I&rsquo;m already happy with my job and I am happy with my salary. After some pondering I thought that extra income would be nice so I tried to give it a shot and I emailed the person back, making it clear that I currently have a full time job and that I would only be able to do this project on my free time. The person then replied back saying that its ok. Then the rest is history. I got the project last April and until now the project is still ongoing so most of my free time goes into that.</p>

<p>Going back to the month of February I also tried emailing Sitepoint, a company dedicated to making awesome articles on web development. It was pretty much a cold email saying that I wanted to write for them. That I&rsquo;ve been writing articles about web development for a while but I&rsquo;ve only been doing it on my blog and that I wanted to try and make money doing it.
I&rsquo;ve waited but I didn&rsquo;t get a reply after a week so I thought they&rsquo;re not interested. But then after exactly a month, the managing editor of Sitepoint PHP Channel emailed me back with an apology for not getting back to me sooner. But the important part is that I got an ok. And man! that was the most awesome feeling ever! Sitepoint is one of the most popular websites which publishes resources (books, articles, courses) on web development. The fact that I get to write for them is really just awesome.</p>

<p>Lastly, I&rsquo;m also occupied with my personal project hoping that it would turn into a nice source of passive income. I can&rsquo;t tell something about the project yet but once I get it out there I&rsquo;ll be publishing a blog post about it so stay tuned for that.</p>

<p>And that&rsquo;s pretty much what I&rsquo;ve been up to lately. I don&rsquo;t think I&rsquo;ll be able to write anything lengthy on blog soon. But I&rsquo;ll try publishing some short tutorials so I still have fresh content in my blog even if I&rsquo;m busy. But basically the series on the Whirlwind tour on Web Developer Tools isn&rsquo;t going to continue soon. I&rsquo;d like to provide as much information as I could on each part of the series. But I don&rsquo;t think I have time to write lengthy posts so I&rsquo;m going to temporarily stop the series.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it for this blog post. At times like this I really wish the <a href="http://dragonball.wikia.com/wiki/Hyperbolic_Time_Chamber">Hyperbolic Time Chamber</a> was for real so I don&rsquo;t need to prioritize things and just do everything I want to do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
