<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: coding | Wern Ancheta]]></title>
  <link href="http://anchetaWern.github.io/blog/categories/coding/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://anchetaWern.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-29T13:49:44+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://anchetaWern.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Wern Ancheta]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons Learned from putting a Software into Production Testing]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetaWern.github.io/blog/2012/12/25/lessons-learned-from-putting-a-software-into-production-testing/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-25T20:09:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetaWern.github.io/blog/2012/12/25/lessons-learned-from-putting-a-software-into-production-testing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ol>
<li>Write Code</li>
<li>Test in the browser</li>
<li>If it works, continue writing another code. If it doesn&rsquo;t, identify what&rsquo;s wrong with the code and debug it.</li>
</ol>


<p>Does these steps look familiar to you? Usually that&rsquo;s enough for small-sized software which only takes 1-2 months to develop. But the same is not true for medium-large sized software which takes 3-12 months to develop.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve made a lot of mistakes when I developed a large size software and here are some of those:</p>

<ul>
<li>No server-side validation</li>
<li>Repeated code everywhere</li>
<li>Procedural code everywhere</li>
<li>Not using MVC</li>
<li>Non-defensive programming</li>
<li>No code written for when things doesn&rsquo;t go as expected (error handlers)</li>
<li>No code written that will handle concurrency</li>
<li>No unit testing</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;ve made a lot of mistakes that I don&rsquo;t want others to repeat again that&rsquo;s why I&rsquo;m writing about it.</p>

<h4>No server-side validation</h4>

<p>Don&rsquo;t write validation code for just the server side or client side alone.
There should be validations written for both the client side and the server side.
This may sound absurd but that&rsquo;s just how things should be.
We need to write client side validation code to automatically inform the user as soon as possible(onKeyUp, onBlur)
if the inputted data is invalid or incorrect.
But we also need to write server side validation to deal with malicious users who can simply disable JavaScript in their browsers to compromise the client side validation. This will also serve as a backup validation in case your client side validation fails you.</p>

<h4>Repeated code everywhere</h4>

<p>Don&rsquo;t just copy and paste code everywhere. Normally you would do this to save time but you&rsquo;re not actually saving time in the long-run. It will be a nightmare maintaining code that has the same code everywhere. This means that if there are some changes in the markup you will have to change the JavaScript code which depends on that markup.
You can say that you won&rsquo;t ever need to make changes but it will always happen. No code is ever written on stone.</p>

<h4>Procedural code everywhere</h4>

<p>You would also want to avoid writing procedural code. You will most likely have to write object oriented code for medium-large sized software to avoid code repetition.
The main idea behind object oriented programming is that you write classes which has member variables and methods that you can reuse later on.</p>

<h4>Not Using MVC</h4>

<p>MVC is basically a way to separate the business logic (computations, how you treat the data) from the presentation (things that the user sees). In other words its a way on how you organize your code so that its easier to find things later on. It usually takes longer to write code that follows the MVC pattern but the time that you will save in maintaining(understanding) code written in this pattern would be the biggest reason why you would want to use it.</p>

<h4>Non-defensive Programming</h4>

<p>You would also want to avoid the mentality that things can&rsquo;t go wrong. Because the truth is they always will(especially on production). Always be a negative thinker when programming. Think of ways in which your code can break.
Think of user inputs that can break through your validation and test them against your code. Always ask the question &ldquo;what if?&rdquo;.</p>

<ul>
<li>What if I enter an sql query that drops the whole table from the database?</li>
<li>What if the server suddenly burns and turns to ashes?</li>
<li>What if the data wasn&rsquo;t backed up and the server is strucked by lightning?</li>
<li>What if the system is used by 1 million users at the same time?</li>
</ul>


<p>Just don&rsquo;t go overboard when asking yourself these questions. Just think of what can possibly happen.</p>

<h4>No code written for when things doesn&rsquo;t go as expected (error handlers)</h4>

<p>Always write code that will handle errors no matter how smoothly you think the software will flow.
It&rsquo;s like the Plan B for when Plan A fails.</p>

<h4>No code written that will handle concurrency</h4>

<p>Always try to see to it that the code that you are writing will be able to handle concurrency.
What I mean by concurrency is that when 10 million users try to register an account on your app at once.
What will happen to the server or the database? Be sure you know how many users will most likely use the software at once then test against it.</p>

<h4>No unit testing</h4>

<p>Lastly there&rsquo;s unit testing. If you&rsquo;re not aware of TDD you should start researching and apply it on your future projects. It&rsquo;s a good way to ensure that the code is really working. You will have to write twice or thrice as much code when applying TDD but the amount of time that you can save in ensuring that a piece of code still works after some modifications and updates would be the main reason why you would want to use TDD.</p>

<p>Those are the things that I hope I knew when I created a large-sized software.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I'm a Terrible Programmer]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetaWern.github.io/blog/2012/12/20/im-a-terrible-programmer/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-20T11:49:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetaWern.github.io/blog/2012/12/20/im-a-terrible-programmer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m a terrible programmer.</p>

<p><strong>I&rsquo;m terrible at naming things</strong>. Sometimes I end up with a very long method name like <code>getAllAwesomePeopleInTheTwitterVerse()</code>.
Or a very short variable like <code>$i</code>.</p>

<p><strong>I don&rsquo;t always follow best practices</strong>.
Yes I know a lot of best practices but I only implement a few of them.
Either because of lack of time to see for myself if its indeed a good practice or just plain laziness.</p>

<p><strong>I do not optimize my code</strong>.
And what I mean by this is that I haven&rsquo;t used profiling tools on my projects
to see if its actually speedy.</p>

<p><strong>I do not use caching</strong>. Queries runs all the time even if there are no changes in the database. I&rsquo;m thinking that not caching the data will not actually affect the performance if there&rsquo;s only a small group of people using the application.</p>

<p><strong>I do not refactor my code all the time</strong>.
Sometimes I end up repeating the logic a few times and then I&rsquo;ll get lazy
and not improve the code.</p>

<p><strong>I use frameworks, libraries and plugins all the time</strong>.
I haven&rsquo;t tried implementing MVC on my own. I use Frameworks like CodeIgniter, CakePHP, Zend, Yii, and Laravel to do things for me.
I use jQuery to manipulate the dom and make the elements dance, sing and fly in the air but I have difficulty implementing it using plain JavaScript.
I always search on Google for the functionality that I need because there may be already a jQuery plugin written for that. Then I&rsquo;ll just hack through the code and modify the stylesheet files if I have to customize something.</p>

<p><strong>I suck at JavaScript</strong>. Yes jQuery is JavaScript and I believe I&rsquo;m good at jQuery but it doesn&rsquo;t necessarily make me a JavaScript developer.
And because of this dependence to jQuery I end up with shitty smelly code full of event delegation and variables polluting the global namespace.
Thankfully I discovered some MV* Frameworks that will hopefully help me with this
shitty client side code problem.
Writing cross-browser JavaScript code is not quite my level yet.</p>

<p><strong>I&rsquo;m terrible at implementing coding standards</strong>.
Sometimes I name my variables like <code>$firstname</code>, sometimes I end up doing
<code>$last_name</code> for the others. One of these days I&rsquo;ll try to research on a tool that can implement coding standards for me. Or at least a text-editor plugin
that will shout at me if it sees anything inconsistent in my code.</p>

<p><strong>I also want to learn a lot</strong>. To the point where I don&rsquo;t know what to learn next anymore. And once I started learning something I couldn&rsquo;t really get to the deeper parts because then I will be interested in learning another thing again.</p>

<p><strong>I don&rsquo;t do Test Driven Development</strong>. Yes I&rsquo;ve wrote a <a href="http://anchetawern.github.com/blog/2012/12/17/getting-started-with-unit-testing-in-php/">tutorial about it</a> and explored some of the basics like assertions, data providers and dependencies but it stopped there. I&rsquo;ve never actually implemented TDD in a project.</p>

<p><strong>I don&rsquo;t do automated testing</strong>. Yes I&rsquo;ve heard of Selenium, Sahi and other automated testing tools but I haven&rsquo;t actually tried them.</p>

<p><strong>I do not use tools</strong> that will make my life easier. Things like yeoman, grunt and bower, IDE with all the shiny new guns and swords.</p>

<p><strong>I do not always ask others</strong> (programmers, developers, ninjas, zombies, robots) opinion on something.</p>

<p><strong>I do not constantly think of the code that I&rsquo;m writing</strong>. Sometimes I just copy and paste
thing here and there. I name variables and methods poorly. And I end up with spaghetti code.</p>

<p><strong>I&rsquo;m having difficulty planning how should I code things</strong>. Something like having a clear picture on how to go about things. Yes I use mockup builders and I write things (system flow, psuedo code) down on paper but I cannot seem to have a clear picture of how to organize my code so that I will need lesser refactoring later on.</p>

<p>Those are the things that makes me believe that I&rsquo;m a terrible programmer.
But I&rsquo;m working on it each day.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
