<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: podcast | Wern Ancheta]]></title>
  <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/categories/podcast/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-10-26T03:54:18+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://wern-ancheta.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Wern Ancheta]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More Podcasts I Listen To]]></title>
    <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2015/10/17/more-podcasts-i-listen-to/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-17T20:53:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2015/10/17/more-podcasts-i-listen-to</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Time flies so fast, I can&rsquo;t believe that its been more than a year since I last posted something about the <a href="/blog/2014/08/31/podcasts-i-listen-to/">podcasts I listen to</a>. Before I was only listening to developer-related podcasts such as Shoptalkshow and Ruby Rogues. But I&rsquo;ve discovered that there are more great podcasts out there outside my own little developer world. Here are some of those:</p>

<h3>Radiolab</h3>

<p>Radiolab is a podcast hosted by Jad Abumrad and Robert Krulwich. It mostly focuses on science and history topics. Its very entertaining and truly a great snack for the brain.</p>

<h3>Developer Tea</h3>

<p>One of the newer podcasts on development produced by Jonathan Cutrell. The thing I really like about this podcast is that its very short, the longest episode I&rsquo;ve heard so far is abou 13 minutes. So it doesn&rsquo;t really take much of your time. You can listen to it while you&rsquo;re on a tea break might be the inspiration why its called developer tea. And because they are short, you can expect to hear only the most essential advice that are useful for you as a developer.</p>

<h3>Nocturne</h3>

<p>Nocturne is a podcast about the night. It features stories of people&rsquo;s experiences in the night. I found out about it when I was searching for scary podcasts. Though I later found out that Nocturne isn&rsquo;t really that. But the quality of the podcast really made me an avid listener.</p>

<h3>Lore</h3>

<p>Lore is a podcast featuring true life scary stories. This includes stories of ghosts and local folklore such as the Jersey Devil.</p>

<h3>NoSleep Podcast</h3>

<p>NoSleep Podcast is a fiction horror podcast. I think its scary but I also think it can be scarier. Though if they would make it more scary, I probably would no longer listen. I think its scariness level is manageable for most people.</p>

<h3>Stuff You Should Know</h3>

<p>A podcast from the howstuffworks.com network. If you have read howstuffworks.com before then you can expect the same kind of content on this podcast. Any topic under the sun which answers the question on how it works.</p>

<h3>Stuff To Blow Your Mind</h3>

<p>As the name suggests, this podcast mainly focuses on stuff that can blow your mind.</p>

<h3>Planet Money</h3>

<p>A podcast from NPR that&rsquo;s all about money and the economy.</p>

<h3>Invisibilia</h3>

<p>A new podcast from NPR which features stories on the invisible forces that control human behavior. I first heard about it while I was listening to Radiolab. I didn&rsquo;t hesitate to try an episode since I already know the quality of podcasts from NPR.</p>

<h3>Last Podcast On The Left</h3>

<p>Yet another podcast that I found while I was looking for scary podcasts. Guess what, Last Podcast On The Left isn&rsquo;t really scary. The Last Podcast On The Left covers all the horrors our world has to offer both imagined and real, from demons and slashers to cults and serial killers, The Last Podcast is guaranteed to satisfy your blood lust. At least that&rsquo;s what their description says. So if you dig those stuff then this podcast is for you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Podcasts I listen to]]></title>
    <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2014/08/31/podcasts-i-listen-to/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-31T07:03:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2014/08/31/podcasts-i-listen-to</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To take a bit of a break from the usual web development tutorials that I published. This week I&rsquo;ll be talking about some of the podcasts that I usually listen to when I&rsquo;m just chilling out doing nothing. Podcasts are a really good way to <a href="/blog/2012/08/16/how-to-stay-updated-as-a-developer/">keep yourself updated as a developer</a> even if you&rsquo;re not in front of a computer.</p>

<h3>Shoptalkshow</h3>

<p>A podcast where they talk about front end web design, development and UX.
Its hosted by Chris Coyier and Dave Rupert. Each week they either interview someone from the industry or have a Rapidfire show in which they answer questions submitted by their listeners.</p>

<h3>Ruby Rogues</h3>

<p>Not like what the name of the podcast suggests, Ruby Rogues isn&rsquo;t exclusively for Ruby stuff. I&rsquo;m not a Ruby Developer myself but I often listen to this podcast because they usually talk about general stuff that developers would want to listen to. Things like <a href="http://rubyrogues.com/171-rr-evaluating-yourself/">self-evaluation</a>, <a href="http://rubyrogues.com/164-rr-staying-sharp-with-dave-thomas/">staying sharp</a>, and <a href="http://rubyrogues.com/163-rr-education-with-coraline-ada-ehmke-and-katrina-owen/">education</a>. They also usually invite someone from the industry to be in the show so that&rsquo;s a bonus as well. At the end of each episode they have a picks section in which each of the hosts pick anything that they want to plug into the show. Such as books, games, a random article.</p>

<h3>JavaScript Jabber</h3>

<p>Pretty much like the Ruby Rogues podcast because its created by the same guy: Charles Maxwood. They mostly invite JavaScript developers to talk about their projects. Such as Guillermo Rauch of Socket.io, Jo Liss of Broccoli.js.</p>

<h3>Freelancer Show</h3>

<p>Another podcast from Charles Maxwood, the Freelancer Show. As the name suggests, its a podcast about freelancing. If you&rsquo;re looking into doing freelancing on your part-time or you want to do freelancing full-time then this podcast is for you.</p>

<h3>Three Devs and a Maybe</h3>

<p>A podcast about Web Development. Though if you visit their website they usually talk about PHP stuff. If you&rsquo;re a PHP developer then this podcast should definitely be on your listening list.</p>

<h3>This Developer&rsquo;s Life</h3>

<p>A podcast about developers and their lives. Though this podcast is not ongoing anymore, most of the things that you&rsquo;ll find in here are still relevant. Its about the daily lives of developers after all. Their content is mostly on story format. And each episode has a specific theme. Things like obsession, learning, competition, getting fired and many others.</p>

<h3>The JavaScript Show</h3>

<p>Though this podcast is no longer active, they have some good stuff in here that you might want to check out. Each episode is fully dedicated to JavaScript stuff, that is both client-side and server-side. Its from the same guy (Peter Cooper) who&rsquo;s curating the contents for the JavaScript Weekly Newsletter so the JavaScript Show is basically a JavaScript Weekly in audio format.</p>

<h3>FaceOff Show</h3>

<p>Another podcast which is no longer active but still pretty useful is the FaceOff Show. They have a total of 126 episodes before they stopped but the content is still available on their website to download or to listen to. The FaceOff Show is a holistic podcast, its basically all of the podcast mentioned above combined into one. In other words, its all thing development.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
