<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: work | Wern Ancheta]]></title>
  <link href="http://anchetaWern.github.io/blog/categories/work/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://anchetaWern.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-08T20:15:13+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://anchetaWern.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Wern Ancheta]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Working Remotely]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetaWern.github.io/blog/2013/04/28/on-working-remotely/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-28T17:52:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetaWern.github.io/blog/2013/04/28/on-working-remotely</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been a year since I started working remotely and I never regret any moment of it. In this post I&rsquo;m going to share some of my thoughts in working remotely. Some of the pros and cons, and how to stay productive even if there&rsquo;s no boss breathing down your neck.</p>

<!--More-->


<p>For those who don&rsquo;t know what telecommuting is. Here&rsquo;s a helpful description from Wikipedia:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Telecommuting, remote work, telework is a work arrangement in which employees do not commute to a central place of work.<br/>A person who telecommutes is known as a &ldquo;telecommuter&rdquo;, &ldquo;teleworker&rdquo;, and sometimes as a &ldquo;home-sourced&rdquo; employee.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Ok now that were on the same page let&rsquo;s begin.</p>

<h3>Pros</h3>

<ul>
<li>Less interruptions.</li>
<li>Less distractions (only if you are disciplined).</li>
<li>Less time wasted on transportation.</li>
<li>Comfortable work environment.</li>
<li>More productive.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Cons</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>No social interactions. Telecommute workers will basically miss out on random office chats and other social events that happens outside the office (E.g. company paid outings).</p></li>
<li><p>There&rsquo;s so little trust. This is basically because the person that you are working with doesn&rsquo;t see if you&rsquo;re really working or not.</p></li>
<li><p>You can&rsquo;t ask for help. Team mates can be working while you&rsquo;re sleeping and most of the time they&rsquo;re too busy with their own work.</p></li>
<li><p>You can&rsquo;t see what other employees in the company are working on. Though this is normal I believe there is a benefit in knowing what projects others are working on especially the senior one&rsquo;s. You know the type of office interaction where you can ask questions to other employees and learn something from their answers.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>How to Stay Productive</h3>

<p>Telecommuting is hard if you don&rsquo;t have the discipline to work without a boss breathing down your neck every second of the day. So the main ingredient needed to successfuly work remotely is discipline.
The kind of discipline that will keep you from looking at your Facebook or Twitter stream every 5 minutes. Or watching some dancing cat ninjas on Youtube. Or endlessly browsing Stumbleupon.</p>

<p>Another important ingredient is love for the work that you do. By loving the work that you do you will have no problem working overtime if you don&rsquo;t think you&rsquo;ve done good enough for the day.</p>

<p>Lastly, you should always have a todo list so that you can keep track of what to do, what&rsquo;s done and what needs some review.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s all there is to it really. You don&rsquo;t need the Pomodoro technique or any other technique to be productive. All you need is discipline and love for your work.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I Like in a Company]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetaWern.github.io/blog/2013/03/10/what-i-like-in-a-company/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-10T10:44:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetaWern.github.io/blog/2013/03/10/what-i-like-in-a-company</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Perhaps this is one of the posts where I share the things I want.
A few alternative titles might be:</p>

<p><blockquote><p><br/><br/>What kind of Companies do I like to work for?</p></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>Things I&rsquo;m looking for in a Company</p></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>What makes a company awesome?</p></blockquote></p>

<!--More-->


<p>I want to work for a company that:</p>

<ul>
<li>Offers a salary that matches my level of competency</li>
<li>Gives a lot of opportunity to grow</li>
<li>Has some nice and awesome people</li>
<li>Gives rasonable deadlines</li>
</ul>


<h3>Offers a salary that matches my level of competency</h3>

<p>As a professional its really important to get paid rightfully with the work that we do.
We do our jobs well and often times we also work beyond the time when we are required to work.
But the exception is that when were just starting out (probably around 1-3 years in the industry)
the priority is to get experience. It doesn&rsquo;t matter if the salary is low because later on
you&rsquo;ll get to demand your salary once you&rsquo;re awesome enough.</p>

<h3>Gives a lot of opportunity to grow</h3>

<p>This is the most important one in the list if you&rsquo;re just starting out.
What I specifically look for in a company is that they&rsquo;re willing to give me work
that involves technologies, tools and methodologies that I do not already know how
to use. This is great because what can you gain from doing things that you already
know over and over and over again? Nothing right?
But you will probably become an expert at doing it.
And you gain the ability to do it blindfolded while your other hand is handcuffed.</p>

<p>Ok going back to the original topic: a company that gives a lot of opportunity to grow.
This is what fresh graduates and people that are fresh in the industry should be looking for.
Because schools only teaches a small fraction of what you would be really working with when you graduate. Its important that you gain the knowledge and experience needed for most of the work that you will be doing in the industry.</p>

<h3>Nice and awesome people</h3>

<p>There will always be douchebags, and people that you can&rsquo;t really work with because of their attitude so its always nice to have some nice people around which are always accomodating, friendly and always ready to answer your questions.
Always offers a piece of advice and always has a suggestion whenever you get yourself in a hole.</p>

<h3>Reasonable Deadlines</h3>

<p>Deadlines are great because it prevents you from working on a project forever.
It prevents you from fooling around while working.
And it keeps you focused on the project.</p>

<p>But some deadlines, especially those that are given by project managers
who have no experience in development are just terrible.</p>

<p>Reasonable deadlines are really important so the developer won&rsquo;t end up
crapifying the code just to catch up to a deadline made for zombie superhumans.
Just like the saying goes:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Everything that is forced ends up like crap</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Its important that the project manager or anyone who&rsquo;s giving out the deadlines
has a prior experience in development.
Because only then can they make an intelligent decision on what the deadline should be.
Even better is letting the developer estimate how much the specific story or module
will take.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>That&rsquo;s it for this blog post. At the end of the day you will always have to choose the company where you&rsquo;re happy to work with and that you&rsquo;re enjoying the work that you do for that company. Otherwise you wouldn&rsquo;t last or even if you stay on that company longer, the work that you do will always be badly affected.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
