<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: essays | Wern Ancheta]]></title>
  <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/categories/essays/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-10-01T12:04:04+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://wern-ancheta.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Wern Ancheta]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I Love Web Development]]></title>
    <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2016/02/03/why-i-love-web-development/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-03T08:56:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2016/02/03/why-i-love-web-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s not very often that I reflect on why I love things. Why I Love Web Development is not a question
I often ask myself. In this essay I&rsquo;ll attempt to explore the why.
I first started learning about Web Development when I was in College.
Back then it was just another subject that I had to learn in order to finish my course.
I never really thought that it would be the thing that puts money in my pocket 5 years later.
I became a Web Developer. It&rsquo;s very easy to get into Web Development. All you need is a computer, a text-editor and a browser.
Just create an HTML file, put some styling into it, and then sprinkle some JavaScript to make things more interactive and you have a full-fledge web page. Of course you&rsquo;ll need to install other things such as Apache, MySQL and PHP if you&rsquo;re working on the back-end.
But initially, Web Development is very accessible for beginners.
With websites such as <a href="https://www.codeschool.com/">Code School</a>, <a href="http://www.pluralsight.com/">Pluralsight</a> and <a href="https://www.codecademy.com/">Codeacademy</a> it became even easier to get into <a href="https://www.codecademy.com/.  ">https://www.codecademy.com/.  </a>
Perhaps that&rsquo;s the first thing that made me fall in love with Web Development. It&rsquo;s easy to get into it. There&rsquo;s also a plethora of information about it. Q&amp;A websites such as <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/">Stackoverflow</a> makes it really easy to solve problems in case you get stuck with something. All you really need to know is to know what to Google.</p>

<p>Web Development isn&rsquo;t without its difficulties. If you&rsquo;re a Web Developer you have to learn so many things.
You have to consider a lot of things when it comes to your users. You need to be empathetic to their needs.
That&rsquo;s probably the reason why there are Web Designers, Front-end Developers, Back-end Developers, Devops and UX Designers. One person can&rsquo;t really do it all. I&rsquo;m not really one to talk because I&rsquo;ve only been practicing Web Development as a Full-stack Developer. Which means that I take care of everything. Or not. I have to admit that I lack the qualities of a Web Designer. And when it comes to UX, I have a lot to learn. I primarily consider myself a Back-end Developer because that&rsquo;s where my core skills are.
But this doesn&rsquo;t mean that I have to ignore learning things about design and how to make things more accessible.
This doesn&rsquo;t mean that I don&rsquo;t need to make an effort no matter how little. Such as putting the <code>alt</code> attribute on images or sprinkling some <code>aria-role</code> attributes in my HTML code. Aside from that, you also need to think about performance. Not all users have a blazing fast internet connection with 10 GB/s download speed. But it doesn&rsquo;t end there. As a developer you also need to think of the maintainability of your code. You need to think of the next person who&rsquo;s going to end up maintaining your code. As a developer you have to make an effort on carefully naming things and structuring your code in such a way that things can easily be found. Your code should also be DRY. Which means that there should only be a single source of truth in your code. And avoid repeating things as much as possible. You need to think about the future. The dependencies you pull into your code. It&rsquo;s always wise to pull in a third-party library to easily accomplish things that would be hard for you to implement on your own. But you also need to make sure that your code doesn&rsquo;t break if this library gets updated.</p>

<p>The idea of creating something that didn&rsquo;t previously exist. The joy of building something and seeing it come to life is what makes Web Development really awesome. You get to play around with shiny, new and cool stuff all the time. You get to learn something new every day. You get to work on side-projects and push it to Github and have other people use your work. That to me is fantastic.</p>

<p>The ability to see the world in a Programmer&rsquo;s eyes. You begin to wonder how things are built. What technologies are behind it? How are things implemented?</p>

<p>The dread that you feel whenever a new JavaScript library comes out. And the fear that the shiny new thing that you&rsquo;ve learned is replaced by that JavaScript library that came out.</p>

<p>The never-ending queue of articles that you think you have to read in order to keep yourself up to date.</p>

<p>The idea that you can reach a lot of people by just creating a single website.
The idea that you can provide valuable information and make their life easier by using the thing that you created. The ability to empower people from a thousand miles a way and they don&rsquo;t even know you. That to me is priceless.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Developers New Years Resolution]]></title>
    <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2016/01/04/a-developers-new-years-resolution/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-04T20:11:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2016/01/04/a-developers-new-years-resolution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s 2016. A brand-new year is upon us. And this is the time of the year when people usually set goals for the new year. While most other folks have new year&rsquo;s resolution for their real life, In this article I&rsquo;ll be sharing some of my new year&rsquo;s resolution as a developer.</p>

<h3>Generate Passive Income</h3>

<p>The idea of generating a passive income has really enticed me in the past but it&rsquo;s only this year that I&rsquo;ve thought about it seriously. For developers one way of generating passive income is through marketplaces like Themeforest and CodeCanyon. All you have to do is build something useful and you can sell it on the platforms that I&rsquo;ve just mentioned. I&rsquo;ve already created an account on CodeCanyon, set it up and read their terms. All that&rsquo;s left for me to do is to build something and submit it for review so that people can find it.</p>

<h3>Continue What I&rsquo;ve Started</h3>

<p>I have a bunch of projects on Github. Some might not already work. Some lacking in documentation. This year I&rsquo;ll continue every project that I started. Or at least mention that I won&rsquo;t already be doing active development for projects that I&rsquo;m no longer interested in pursuing.</p>

<p>I have also a blog series that I started back in 2014 which I called: <a href="http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2014/02/09/a-whirlwind-tour-of-web-developer-tools/">A Whirlwind Tour of Web Developer Tools</a>, I&rsquo;m planning to start that up again this year.</p>

<h3>Be More Picky</h3>

<p>I read a lot. In fact I&rsquo;ve created <a href="http://updatedapp.github.io/">a website</a> that curates all the news from sources that I want. Usually these are from the developer newsletters, twitter users, and websites that I follow.
But I&rsquo;m still subscribed to the newsletters which I have used as the news item source. So it still gets the better of my time when I receive a new issue. My plan is to unsubscribe to all of those newsletters and just stick to using the website myself. This is so that I don&rsquo;t accidentally engage to some content. Or click on a link and not actually reading what&rsquo;s in there. With the new setup I can actually just visit the website if I really want to read something and not when I receive a new issue of a newsletter.</p>

<p>The second step after unsubscribing to all newsletters is to actually pick only what I really want to read. If its a tool that I can use in the future, then I save it on my delicious account. If its an article which I want to go back to in the future then I save it on Pocket.</p>

<p>The third step is to actually read what&rsquo;s really important or at least something that I really want to read. Of course this can&rsquo;t be determined by merely looking at the title so the article has to be scanned first and then determine if it&rsquo;s really relevant.</p>

<p>Of course this goes with all the other content that I&rsquo;m consuming and creating. So movies, anime shows, personal projects, blog posts should go through a tight consideration before I actually engage on it.</p>

<h3>Be More Healthy</h3>

<p>Developers have a sedentary lifestyle by nature. Just sitting on a chair coding all day. That&rsquo;s no good so here are the steps that I&rsquo;m planning to implement to be more healthy.</p>

<ul>
<li>Indoor exercise in the morning. Intense outdoor exercise in the weekends.</li>
<li>Use the standing desk at least one hour in the morning and one hour in the afternoon.</li>
<li>Eat less rice.</li>
<li>Eat more fruits and vegetables. There should be at least one meal per day where I eat a decent amount of those.</li>
<li>Get more sunlight.</li>
<li>Sleep more.</li>
<li>Be more concious about my posture.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Engage More in the Community</h3>

<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ll start by creating videos <a href="http://youtube.com/WernAncheta">on Youtube</a> showing a specific technology, tool or methodology regarding web development. I&rsquo;ve already started it the previous year by uploading some of my flipped classroom videos that I&rsquo;ve used in my class in the school where I teach.</li>
<li>Comment on other developers blog posts, or talk to them on twitter.</li>
<li>Answer questions on Stackoverflow.</li>
<li>Attend local developer meetups.</li>
<li>Contribute to open-source projects.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Use Tools</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been pretty much avoiding the use of tools in my day to day job as a developer. I still use plain css instead of Less, Sass, Stylus or {insert your css preprocessor of choice here}. I still don&rsquo;t use Grunt, Gulp, Brocolli, Carrots, Eggplant, {insert your build tool of choice here} for every project (note: there&rsquo;s no carrots or eggplant yet but someone might create it after this). I&rsquo;ve been avoiding the use of tools because I just want to get started with a project fast. Installing a bunch of tools and setting them up before I can start coding is a pain. The only tools that I currently use are the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Composer</li>
<li>Bower</li>
<li>npm</li>
</ul>


<p>Simply because you can&rsquo;t install anything without those.</p>

<p>This year I&rsquo;ll start by learning how to use Yeoman so I can easily setup all the things that I need for a project. And then learn how to use a css preprocessor, Gulp to process the project assets, JSLint to check the quality of my JavaScript code. And then in the back-end use PHPUnit for unit-testing.
And lastly use a continuous integration server such as Jenkins to automatically run unit tests so that I immediately know if a specific code is still working or not.</p>

<h3>Build More Cool Shit</h3>

<p>Pardon the language but developers are <a href="https://twitter.com/gitlost">commonly foul-mouthed</a> right? Anyway, what I mean by build more cool shit is to create stuff that I can be proud of. I&rsquo;d also like to build IOT (Internet of Things) projects. And with the birth of the RaspberryPi zero it just got more easy. Though I&rsquo;m yet to order one because the stock is always zero. I should have ordered one when I first heard about it. Now people are ordering it non-stop. Who wouldn&rsquo;t right? RaspberryPi zero is only five fucking dollars.</p>

<h3>Learn a New Language, Framework, Tool, Methodology</h3>

<ul>
<li>Language: Python &ndash; If I am to build stuff with RaspberryPi I need to learn to code in Python. I also want to leap from the hybrid app bandwagon and go full native so I&rsquo;ll have to learn (or rather re-learn) Java. This is simply because apps built with Hybrid App Framework such as Cordova performs poorly on my old android phone. Maybe I just need a new phone but I&rsquo;ll go ahead and blame it to programming.</li>
<li>Framework: Symfony &ndash; I&rsquo;m basically a Laravel guy so for a change I pick Symfony.</li>
<li>Tools: CI Server, PHPUnit, Gulp, Sass, ReactJS</li>
<li>Methodology: I&rsquo;m still not sure. But I&rsquo;ll probably try to learn some of the most popular design patterns in JavaScript and PHP.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Get Better at What I Do</h3>

<p>No matter how good you are at something there&rsquo;s always room for improvement, there&rsquo;s always another way for doing things twice as easy or efficient. So the plan for 2016 is to look for ways to improve my current development workflow. Like I said earlier I&rsquo;m a Laravel guy so I&rsquo;ll start by examining my current Laravel workflow and see what I can improve.</p>

<h3>Invade Other Fields</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been really interested in UX because I know it will be helpful for me as an all-around developer. When I say all-around it means I&rsquo;m the one doing the server setup up to deployment and anything between those two. I&rsquo;m pretty much a one-man band in all the projects that I&rsquo;ve built so far. No devops, no designer, no nothing.</p>

<p>Another field that I&rsquo;d like to look into is SEO. Who wouldn&rsquo;t want to have their website more findable?</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it! How about you? What&rsquo;s your plan for 2016?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Playing Clash of Clans Can Teach You About Life]]></title>
    <link href="http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2015/08/23/what-playing-clash-of-clans-can-teach-you-about-life/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-23T12:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2015/08/23/what-playing-clash-of-clans-can-teach-you-about-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ol>
<li><p><strong>You need to prioritize</strong>. There&rsquo;s only like 2 or 3 builder huts when you start playing the game.
That&rsquo;s why it&rsquo;s important to prioritize which things you upgrade. This is because upgrading takes time. And cancelling an upgrade will only return you half of the original resources you spent on the upgrade.
This usually means there&rsquo;s no turning back after you&rsquo;ve clicked on that upgrade button.
Just like in life you have to prioritize. You can&rsquo;t just aimlessly be doing everything that seems interesting.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>You need the right strategy for every raid that you do</strong>. Not every base is the same. There are those whose traps are laid outside the walls. This usually means that it will be triggered the moment your troops lay their first step to loot the resources. There are traps that are laid right before key defenses such as the mortar or air defense. Just like in life you need to carefully plan out your every move, especially the most important one&rsquo;s such as career decisions.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>You can&rsquo;t protect everything</strong>. Put your town hall outside in order to protect what&rsquo;s really important. Some players might disagree to this and say that if you have designed your base well then that&rsquo;s the ultimate defense that keeps other players from attacking your village. Some players might also be prioritizing trophies instead of loots and that&rsquo;s why they keep their town halls at the very center of their village. Those are all valid arguments. Some players might value trophies more than the loots. But come to think of it. There&rsquo;s over 6 million people who have it installed on Android. I don&rsquo;t know about iOS but 6 million people is a lot. This means that no matter how strong you think your village is. There&rsquo;s always someone who can 3-star it effortlessly and take away a ton of loot. So it&rsquo;s important to realize that you can&rsquo;t protect everything. You have to prioritize what you really want to protect and design your village in such a way that what you want to protect is protected in the best possible way. Just like in life you can&rsquo;t get everything that you want. It&rsquo;s important to love what you currently have.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>There&rsquo;s always someone out there whose stronger than you</strong>. There&rsquo;s no need to feel bad whenever some other 3-starred your village. Just like in life you don&rsquo;t need to feel bad about yourself whenever you see someone who is effortlessly better than you at the thing you&rsquo;re good at. What&rsquo;s important is that you work hard to get better each day.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Revenge is for the weak</strong>. I don&rsquo;t know for other players but I pretty much don&rsquo;t care about other players attacking my village. It doesn&rsquo;t really matter whether they 3-starred me or they took a whole bunch of loot. They&rsquo;re just playing the game just like me. It&rsquo;s natural for your village to get attacked. It&rsquo;s natural for other players to take some resources out of your village. Just like it&rsquo;s natural for you take others as well. But maybe it&rsquo;s just me. I heard you would get a lot more trophies if you revenge on someone. But trophies aren&rsquo;t really important to me. I pretty much gave up on trying to go higher when I reached the crystal league. I tried going higher in order to get the gems as the reward but it&rsquo;s just hard to look for town halls that are unprotected.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Time is money but you can also use money to buy time</strong>. When I gave up on reaching the master league in order to get the gem reward for reaching it. And eventually buy the 5th builder with it. I just bought some gems with some real money in order to buy the 5th builder. I don&rsquo;t really regret it since I just saved myself a lot of time trying to find unprotected town halls and get a measely amount of trophy. This is an example of buying time with money. With the 5th builder upgrades would be faster. And I no longer need to aim to get the gem reward for entering the master, champion, titan or legend leagues.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Patience</strong>. Upgrades takes time, creating troops and spells takes time. Gold mines, elixir collectors, heck dark elixir drills takes time. Heroes takes time to sleep. Cool-down for requesting clan castle troops takes time. Searching for a good village to raid takes time. Patience is really a virtue. Especially so when it comes to playing clash of clans. Where every move you do takes time.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Collaboration</strong>. It&rsquo;s important to collaborate with your clan mates during a war. You can&rsquo;t always have a mirror that directly matches yours. Often times your mirror is far stronger than you are. Sometimes the town hall doesn&rsquo;t even match. That&rsquo;s why it&rsquo;s important to collaborate with your clan mates so that you can adjust accordingly. Just like in life it&rsquo;s important to collaborate with your fellow employees, with your community and with your family.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Progress will come naturally if you just stick to it</strong>. When I first started I really envied my friends on facebook because their villages looks so strong and tough and mine looks really week. But 6 months later I saw that my village is pretty much already on par with them or even stronger. I&rsquo;m not addicted to the game though. I really only play on my free time. But I always stick to it every day. And that is why I can see that I&rsquo;ve come a long way since I first started. This is similar to anything that you want to achieve in life. As a developer I always see to it that I learn something new each day. Or have a better understanding of what I previously learned. Just stick to doing something each day and progress will come naturally.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Even heroes needs sleep</strong>. So do you. Sleep is needed in order to recharge your mind and body. The brain needs sleep in order to consolidate the things you&rsquo;ve learned during the day. So even if you think you&rsquo;re a superhero who only needs 3 hours of sleep in order to get by. You&rsquo;re not. You can&rsquo;t really hack your way out of sleep. That&rsquo;s what makes us human. We need rest in order to recharge.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Donate and you will be rewarded</strong>. In clash of clans there is this donation system wherein a clan member can ask for troops to be put in the clan castle. Those troops will serve as guards for your village. If you always donate troops whenever someone asks for it, you will be remembered and your clan mates would love to donate troops to you as well. The same is true in life as well. Always donate to the less fortunate people and you will be rewarded.</p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
