<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: thoughts | Wern Ancheta]]></title>
  <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/categories/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-07T09:03:22+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Wern Ancheta]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Plans for 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2015/01/10/plans-for-2015/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-10T10:56:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2015/01/10/plans-for-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Its 2015 and I think the best way to start one&rsquo;s year right is to lay out some plans. This 2015 I want to be more ambitious with the side projects that I do, I want to make my head hurt a little more. Because that&rsquo;s the only way to grow as a developer. I also want to read more books, watch more video courses and write more this 2015.</p>

<h3>Side Projects</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Anime API</strong> &ndash; I&rsquo;m a really big fan of anime. I watch anime everyday. That&rsquo;s why I&rsquo;m thinking of creating an API about anime. It will be something like <a href="http://www.imdb.com/">IMDb</a> but for anime. It will include information such as the title, genre, cover image, plot, air dates, and links to relevant websites.</li>
<li><strong>Pokemon API</strong> &ndash; Pokemon is one of the things I grew up with. Starting from the Red Version on Gameboy Color up to the Pokemon X Version on 3DS. There&rsquo;s already an existing <a href="http://pokeapi.co">Pokemon API</a> which is really good, except the fact that its lacking some data. Specifically on base stats, in-game trainers, type defenses, moves learned and pokedex entries. I want an API which has all of the information you need to know about Pokemon.</li>
<li><strong>Antares</strong> &ndash; At the later part of 2014 I published this <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.wern.antares">app on google play</a>. Its a news reader for developers. Currently its only getting news from various newsletters that I subscribe to, hacker news, medium, readability and other developer websites. I&rsquo;m planning to add machine learning capabilities to it so it will only recommend links that are more interesting to the current user.</li>
<li><strong>Ahead</strong> &ndash; As I&rsquo;ve introduced before, <a href="/blog/2014/09/28/introduction-to-ahead/">ahead</a> is an app for scheduling posts to be published later to twitter, facebook or linkedin. I&rsquo;m thinking of adding integration to delicious, readability or instapaper. Or maybe get some data from the antares api and have it recommend some links for the user to share.</li>
<li><strong>vid-master</strong> &ndash; This is a project I started 5 months ago in the company that I&rsquo;m currently working for. Its a laravel app for creating video websites, this allows the user to import videos from youtube or vimeo and then use those as the content for the video website. Unfortunately this got abandoned so I asked my boss if I could just open-source it. And he agreed, that&rsquo;s why its now on my <a href="https://github.com/anchetaWern/vid-master">Github</a> waiting for updates.</li>
</ul>


<p>Those are my ideas for now. I&rsquo;ve already mentioned some of the projects that I&rsquo;m planning to do in my <a href="/blog/2014/11/22/brain-dump-0/">brain dump post</a>.</p>

<h3>Code Quality</h3>

<p>As developers were in a constant pressure of releasing stuff out in the open. And that is true for me as well. Most of the time I sacrifice quality for the sake of speed. So that I can release things fast. That is why this 2015 I&rsquo;ll try to write more quality code whenever possible. I won&rsquo;t proceed with the first solution that comes to mind because that&rsquo;s often the hacky solution which results in dirty code. I&rsquo;ll also try to learn about design patterns, inversion of control, dependency injection, and leverage existing libraries more.</p>

<h3>Articles</h3>

<p>Aside from the ones I already mentioned on <a href="/blog/2014/11/22/brain-dump-0/">brain dump</a>. I&rsquo;m thinking of doing the following as well:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Laravel Series</strong> &ndash; as I&rsquo;m mainly using laravel for most of my projects I think its necessary for me to write about it to further enforce what I&rsquo;ve learned and to share it to others.</li>
<li><strong>Shopify Series</strong> &ndash; I want to learn more about Shopify since I&rsquo;ve been getting lots of Shopify projects lately. Because of this article that I&rsquo;ve written 2 years ago about <a href="http://wern-ancheta.com/blog/2013/11/09/getting-started-with-shopify-app-development/">getting started with shopify app development</a>. I had to decline all of those projects since I&rsquo;m not confident enough on my Shopify Development skills. And so I think that doing more Shopify is the only solution. And I&rsquo;ll document everything that I learn on this blog in a form of a series of articles discussing about various Shopify topics.</li>
<li><strong>Prediction IO Series</strong> &ndash; just like Shopify, I&rsquo;m also getting a lot of projects concerning Prediction IO. So I also want to dive deeper so that I can feel confident enough about taking projects.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Screencast</h3>

<p>I had this plan for many years now but I never really got to put it into action. Hopefully this year I will get to create a new youtube channel such as <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/thenewboston">thenewboston</a> or <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/phpacademy">phpacademy</a> to share the things that I&rsquo;ve learned by means of a video. I think I really need this to exercise my verbal communication skills because as a remote and sole developer I don&rsquo;t really need to talk that much to do my job.</p>

<h3>Health</h3>

<p>Two years ago I wrote this blog post on <a href="/blog/2013/05/11/how-to-stay-healthy-as-a-developer/">how to stay healthy as a developer</a>. As you might already know being a developer or any other job that requires you to sit all day long is bad for the health. That&rsquo;s why this 2015 I want to be a healthier person by means of walking. Walking is a very good physical activity that requires less effort. I recently bought a <a href="https://www.fitbit.com/">fitbit flex</a> which allows me to track the number of steps I&rsquo;ve made and the calories I&rsquo;ve burned. Hopefully this will help me to walk more and keep me motivated.</p>

<h3>Time Management</h3>

<p>I watch a lot of anime (6 to 14 titles per season), I waste a lot of time reading articles that I think matters, I like to keep up with a lot of things which ends up consuming most of my free time (Twitter, Facebook, Hacker News, Podcasts). This 2015 I want to be more picky about the things I watch and read so that I can have more time to do what&rsquo;s really important.</p>

<p>I think that pretty much sums it up. Looking forward for a productive and bountiful 2015.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2015/01/04/why-i-code/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-04T08:50:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2015/01/04/why-i-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Why I code? I&rsquo;ve been thinking about this lately. Why is it that I love coding? What is it about coding that keeps me from doing it? What makes it so special? How do I maintain my love for coding even if its so frustrating most of the time. When I was younger I was into drawing. Cartoon characters, robots, sceneries, abstract art, and anything else that picked my interest. Not a week would past that I haven&rsquo;t added a new drawing in my collection. What kept me drawing back then was the sheer joy of adding a new drawing in my collection. It was sort of addictive. I couldn&rsquo;t wait to fill that old magazine with my drawings. In the end I ended up filling up about 8 old magazines with about 50 drawings each. Why did I stopped? It was around college days that I stopped drawing entirely. Mainly because of how busy it was and I really wanted to concentrate on my studies. College was my very first introduction to coding. The first programming language that I&rsquo;ve learned was c++. I easily picked up coding at first because we were just assigning variables and outputting strings. But as we dive deeper into adding actual logic in the programs that we wrote in our class, that&rsquo;s when my head started to hurt. I remember spending about 3 hours on our first project without making any progress. That was the dark ages when I didn&rsquo;t know how to ask Google for answers. Back then I never thought I&rsquo;d be doing coding as a primary source of work. I thought it was too difficult. Maybe I&rsquo;ll just do animation and stuff. But hey, Computer Programming was a major subject that I needed to pass. So it just came naturally that I needed to do something about it. That was when I started to take some of my free time and use it to practice writing some code. I took some of the exercises that we were having and tried to write it from scratch without looking at any of the notes. Once I&rsquo;ve successfully implemented it, I added some features. That was also when my Googling skills started to improve, as I needed some useful answers to the problems that I was having. Then I also discovered something that will change my life forever. Stackoverflow. I joined Stackoverflow in hopes that it will provide me some answers to the problems that I was having. Before I knew it, I have already asked about a hundred questions. Most of them with some useful answers from the community. Some were marked as a duplicate question, some were marked as non-useful or out of scope. Either way the comments and answers were really useful. Sometimes even the comments are enough.</p>

<p>Over time I got better at coding. I started to feel confident about my coding skills. I started believing that I could actually do this for a job. As I started to know more about programming and gain more experience. I realized just how much I still don&rsquo;t know. That&rsquo;s the time when I started my very first blog which I would write about some of the things that I&rsquo;ve learned in my coding adventures. At first I was writing about some VB.Net CRUD things. Because that was what they were teaching at school. I also wrote about some Java stuff when it was taught. Then came Web Development. HTML, CSS, JavaScript, PHP and MySQL. And I taught to myself. Dude! this is pretty sweet! I could write a program and have it used by many people as long as they&rsquo;re connected to the internet. That&rsquo;s when we were introduced to w3schools and htmlgoodies. These websites quickly became my best friend. They were my number one source of web stuff for a long time. But then came w3fools. Which made me realize that w3schools actually sucks. I started using MDN as my primary reference for web stuff as w3fools recommended.</p>

<p>Fast-forward to the present. I am now calling myself a web developer. Specifically a full-stack developer. Responsible for almost everything that&rsquo;s needed to release a whole website out in the open. I&rsquo;m a web developer for about 2 years now. Mainly doing some remote work. And sometimes freelancing on the side. And that leads us to the original question. Why I code? That&rsquo;s mainly because it gives you the ability to reach thousands of people and make their lives easier through the use of the app that you&rsquo;ve written. Its the joy of creating something out of nothing. The challenges that you encounter as you try to build your app. That rewarding feeling that you get when you finally implemented that feature which made your brain explode. Or that feeling that you got when you finally solved that bug that&rsquo;s been haunting you for 10 hours. Its also about the excitement that you feel whenever there&rsquo;s a shiny new toy that comes out. The shiny new toy can be any library, framework or programming language that was released recently. Finally, I code because I want to leave something to the world that will prove my existence. That I have onced lived and created this useful website or app that has been useful to many people. I&rsquo;m still far from that realization though. Like I said earlier, my side projects mainly solve a specific problem that I&rsquo;m having. And the projects that I&rsquo;m getting from the company I&rsquo;m currently working for are targeted only for a specific group of people and country. At most there will only be hundreds of people who will be able to use it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Always scratch your developer itch]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2014/10/25/always-scratch-your-developer-itch/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-25T07:31:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2014/10/25/always-scratch-your-developer-itch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As developers, no matter how busy we are with our lives, its important for us to always scratch our developer itches every now and then. What I mean by itches are the things that you want to do as a developer. Be it working on a side-project that you&rsquo;ve been wanting to do for months, playing with a new technology, library or a programming language. Or reading an in-depth article about a new programming technique. Or watching a video tutorial about a framework that you&rsquo;ve been wanting to learn. Or watching recorded talks from developer conferences all over the world. Or writing an article about a cool technique you&rsquo;ve discovered recently. And other things that you always have at the back of your mind but never really got to do because of lack of time.</p>

<p>Lack of time is always the reason we give to ourselves. But time is not really the problem. We can always make time for something if we really love to do it. Yes we also have lives to live. But we also need to give priority to the things that matter to us as a developer. As a developers, we have the responsibility for continuous learning. To improve our craft for the better. And this is what it means to scratch your developer itch. If you have it, you&rsquo;ll always find time to scratch it no matter how busy you may be.</p>

<p>On the contrary, we also have lives to live. Nothing is more important than our families and our lives as actual people. So giving time to that is our priority as a human being. After all life is not all about work. Life is about living it in the best way possible. And that is through spending quality time with our loved one&rsquo;s.</p>

<p>In conclusion, its really all about balance. If you can&rsquo;t find time every weekend to scratch your own developer itch, then maybe do it once or twice a month. Maybe 4-8 hours twice a month doing a side project is a good start. You can also go to work early and read up on blogs before and after the alloted time for work. Listen to podcasts while commuting. Most podcasts provide download links to each episode which you can save into your mp3 player of smartphone. Watching a 5-minute video tutorial just before going to bed. Every bit of time counts. It doesn&rsquo;t matter how little or how much, what&rsquo;s important is to give time to scratch our developer itches whenever we can. If you do, you&rsquo;ll be a happier developer. Its like the feeling you get when you were finally able to get what you&rsquo;ve been wanting to buy for a long time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Driving]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2014/10/12/on-driving/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-12T18:24:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2014/10/12/on-driving</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Its been a month since I started to learn how to drive. In this blog post I want to touch a bit on what I learned about driving so far.</p>

<h3>Before Starting</h3>

<ul>
<li>Check the wheels if they are on good condition.</li>
<li>Make sure that both side mirrors are set.</li>
<li>Make sure that the hand brake isn&rsquo;t currently active. In most cars all you have to do is hold the brake, press the button with your thumb and then push the lever down.</li>
<li>Just before you use the ignition key to turn on the engine, fully hold down the foot brake, set the car from park (P) to drive (D), then slowly release the foot brake.</li>
<li>Always remember to start slow. Apply as little pressure to the gas pedal as possible.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Overtaking</h3>

<ul>
<li>Don&rsquo;t try to overtake if you&rsquo;re not sure if there&rsquo;s an approaching vehicle on the other lane.</li>
<li>Do not try to overtake on curves.</li>
<li>Do not try to overtake inside a town or a city.</li>
<li>Before trying to overtake a vehicle, check both side mirrors if there&rsquo;s any other vehicle also trying to overtake.</li>
<li>Use the left signal light before trying to overtake to let others know that you&rsquo;re trying to overtake. Once you&rsquo;ve succeeded, use the right signal light and then go back to your lane.</li>
<li>When another vehicle tries to overtake yours, slow down a bit.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Emergencies</h3>

<ul>
<li>When an ambulance or police car is approaching or coming from your back, keep up with your normal speed and move the car to the side of the road to let them pass.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Curves</h3>

<ul>
<li>Slow down before approaching curves to avoid possible collision.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Intersections</h3>

<ul>
<li>Always slow down before approaching intersections. Around 20-30 kph. This is to make sure you don&rsquo;t collide with other vehicles. You can never really know what approaches you in intersections so slow down.</li>
</ul>


<h3>U-turn</h3>

<ul>
<li>When going from one lane to the other make sure that u-turn is allowed.</li>
<li>If you want to give yourself more space, park your car on the side of the road first then when the road is clear, maneuver the wheel to the left. Most of the time you&rsquo;ll have to turn the wheel to the left until its limit. If it isn&rsquo;t enough, stop the car with the foot brake and then use reverse mode to move the car backwards a bit. Use the foot brake again and then turn the car to drive mode and turn the wheel to the left as much as its needed. Just before the car is completely facing in the right direction, turn the wheel to the right until its in its neutral position. Most wheels in modern cars actually go back to neutral position automatically but its safer if you don&rsquo;t rely on that. Because most of the time you&rsquo;ll want to move it to neutral position as fast as you can.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Speed</h3>

<ul>
<li>Don&rsquo;t try to go faster than what you can handle. My personal limit is 60 kph, I don&rsquo;t try to go faster than that.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Rough Road</h3>

<ul>
<li>If you actually care for your car, slow down when approaching rough roads.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Horn</h3>

<ul>
<li>Only use the horn when its absolutely necessary. Sometimes its prohibited to use it on some areas.</li>
<li>Do not use the horn to vent out your frustration. An example of this is when bicycle riders or sidewalk vendors use the road as if they were riding a car. Just give the horn a light tap, and if the bicycle rider still doesn&rsquo;t move to the side simply go pass them if the situation allows.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Stay Cool</h3>

<ul>
<li>Be sure to keep your head cool at all times. You don&rsquo;t want your driving to be affected because of your frustration.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Parking</h3>

<ul>
<li>Be sure that you are only parking your car where it is allowed.</li>
<li>Completely stop the car with the foot brake before putting the car into park mode and pulling the hand brake.</li>
<li>Be sure to leave enough space to maneuver your car later on. You don&rsquo;t want to get to close to another car to avoid scratching it.</li>
<li>If the situation allows, use reverse mode when parking your car, this means that the tail of your car goes inside and the head is outside. This makes it easier for you to go out later on.</li>
</ul>


<p>That&rsquo;s it! I&rsquo;m still a beginner at this so I&rsquo;ll be adding more things to this blog post in future as I learn more things about driving. For now I&rsquo;m going to leave you with this saying:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Better late than dead.</p></blockquote></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Being a dark matter developer must be nice]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2014/03/12/being-a-dark-matter-developer-must-be-nice/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-12T11:45:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2014/03/12/being-a-dark-matter-developer-must-be-nice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It must be nice to be a dark matter developer. But before I go ahead and start going through why its nice to be a dark matter developer let&rsquo;s make sure that were all on the same boat. First what are dark matter developers?</p>

<ul>
<li>they don&rsquo;t read blogs</li>
<li>they don&rsquo;t write blogs</li>
<li>they don&rsquo;t follow Paul Irish on Twitter</li>
<li>they don&rsquo;t release code on Github</li>
<li>they only learn what their boss told them to learn</li>
<li>they don&rsquo;t know what hacker news is</li>
<li>they don&rsquo;t discuss tech outside of work</li>
<li>they don&rsquo;t go to conferences</li>
<li>they only use stackoverflow to seek answers</li>
<li>they don&rsquo;t listen to podcasts</li>
<li>they don&rsquo;t need to update themselves of the cutting edge</li>
<li>they don&rsquo;t experiment on different technologies</li>
<li>they don&rsquo;t learn on their free time</li>
<li>they don&rsquo;t subscribe to newsletters</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;m not saying that this is true for all dark matter developers. But most of the items above are definitely true for some developers even if they don&rsquo;t necessarily consider themselves DMD&rsquo;s.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h4>Ok so why?</h4>

<ul>
<li>they have lots of time in their hands for the really important things in life (family, friends, hobbies, etc.)</li>
<li>they don&rsquo;t need to filter through all the noise in tech (twitter news feed, newsletters, podcasts etc)</li>
<li>they get their job done</li>
</ul>


<p>Let me dive into it a little bit.</p>

<h4>They have lots of time in their hands</h4>

<p>DMD&rsquo;s are free to use all of their free time with the things they want to do. They can just indulge in their hobbies, spend some quality time with their families or just watch season 1-9 of Supernatural or God of Thrones with no care in the world. DMD&rsquo;s also don&rsquo;t need to care about the time they spend doing these activities so they can totally immerse themselves and enjoy their time. They don&rsquo;t need to worry whether they are already outdated. To them programming is just a job. And surely they don&rsquo;t want to code outside their job. I believe its a good thing. Because they can spend all their free time without ever worrying if they will get left behind.</p>

<h4>They don&rsquo;t need to filter through all the noise in tech</h4>

<p>DMD&rsquo;s don&rsquo;t care about all the crap that&rsquo;s happening in the tech scene. They don&rsquo;t know what Shoptalk Show, Ruby Rogues or JavaScript Jabber is. They don&rsquo;t know Paul Irish, Ilya Grigorik, Addy Osmani, Steve Souders, Nicole Sullivan, Peter Cooper, or Jeffrey Way is. They haven&rsquo;t subscribed to JavaScript Weekly, HTML5 Weekly, Web Design Weekly or StatusCode. They only know what they need to know or what they need to know in order to get their job done. They&rsquo;re only consuming the minimal information needed to survive as a developer. Again I believe its a good thing. Sometimes most of the information from these sources are really unimportant.</p>

<h4>They get their job done</h4>

<p>Lastly they get their job done and they do it well. Sure they might still be using Dreamweaver (or maybe notepad) in building websites but they get the job done. They might be cranking out procedural code here and there but they&rsquo;re getting the job done. They might not know what TDD or BDD is. They might not know what linting or static code analysis is but they get the job done. They might not be using the tools (Sublime Test, Chrome Dev Tools, Grunt, SASS, CoffeeScript, Backbone, Angular, Node) that all the cool kids in town are using but they get the job done. They might not be using Frameworks but their code is fast as hell. They might not be writing tests for their code but their program works. They get their job done without ever worrying if their practices are already outdated. Or the tools that they are using can still be improved in order for them to be more productive. I believe there&rsquo;s a beauty in this because they can just focus on the task at hand like painters or artists.</p>

<h4>Closing Thoughts</h4>

<p>Of course with anything there are downsides but I just wanted to focus on the positive side of being a Dark Matter Developer in this post. Cheers to all the Dark Matter Developer&rsquo;s out there! Even if you might not read this because you&rsquo;re always busy getting things done.</p>

<h3>More on DMD&rsquo;s</h3>

<p>If you want to read more about Dark Matter Developers, Scott Hanselman wrote a pretty good post about it: <a href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/DarkMatterDevelopersTheUnseen99.aspx">Dark Matter Developers: The Unseen 99%</a>.
Another good one is Mat McLoughlin&rsquo;s: <a href="http://mat-mcloughlin.net/2013/11/26/dark-matter-developers-do-not-equal-bad-developers/#.VEGf_h_vYes">Dark Matter Developer != Bad Developers</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
