<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: driving | Wern Ancheta]]></title>
  <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/categories/driving/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-03T10:25:12+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Wern Ancheta]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Driving]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2014/10/12/on-driving/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-12T18:24:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2014/10/12/on-driving</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Its been a month since I started to learn how to drive. In this blog post I want to touch a bit on what I learned about driving so far.</p>

<h3>Before Starting</h3>

<ul>
<li>Check the wheels if they are on good condition.</li>
<li>Make sure that both side mirrors are set.</li>
<li>Make sure that the hand brake isn&rsquo;t currently active. In most cars all you have to do is hold the brake, press the button with your thumb and then push the lever down.</li>
<li>Just before you use the ignition key to turn on the engine, fully hold down the foot brake, set the car from park (P) to drive (D), then slowly release the foot brake.</li>
<li>Always remember to start slow. Apply as little pressure to the gas pedal as possible.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Overtaking</h3>

<ul>
<li>Don&rsquo;t try to overtake if you&rsquo;re not sure if there&rsquo;s an approaching vehicle on the other lane.</li>
<li>Do not try to overtake on curves.</li>
<li>Do not try to overtake inside a town or a city.</li>
<li>Before trying to overtake a vehicle, check both side mirrors if there&rsquo;s any other vehicle also trying to overtake.</li>
<li>Use the left signal light before trying to overtake to let others know that you&rsquo;re trying to overtake. Once you&rsquo;ve succeeded, use the right signal light and then go back to your lane.</li>
<li>When another vehicle tries to overtake yours, slow down a bit.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Emergencies</h3>

<ul>
<li>When an ambulance or police car is approaching or coming from your back, keep up with your normal speed and move the car to the side of the road to let them pass.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Curves</h3>

<ul>
<li>Slow down before approaching curves to avoid possible collision.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Intersections</h3>

<ul>
<li>Always slow down before approaching intersections. Around 20-30 kph. This is to make sure you don&rsquo;t collide with other vehicles. You can never really know what approaches you in intersections so slow down.</li>
</ul>


<h3>U-turn</h3>

<ul>
<li>When going from one lane to the other make sure that u-turn is allowed.</li>
<li>If you want to give yourself more space, park your car on the side of the road first then when the road is clear, maneuver the wheel to the left. Most of the time you&rsquo;ll have to turn the wheel to the left until its limit. If it isn&rsquo;t enough, stop the car with the foot brake and then use reverse mode to move the car backwards a bit. Use the foot brake again and then turn the car to drive mode and turn the wheel to the left as much as its needed. Just before the car is completely facing in the right direction, turn the wheel to the right until its in its neutral position. Most wheels in modern cars actually go back to neutral position automatically but its safer if you don&rsquo;t rely on that. Because most of the time you&rsquo;ll want to move it to neutral position as fast as you can.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Speed</h3>

<ul>
<li>Don&rsquo;t try to go faster than what you can handle. My personal limit is 60 kph, I don&rsquo;t try to go faster than that.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Rough Road</h3>

<ul>
<li>If you actually care for your car, slow down when approaching rough roads.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Horn</h3>

<ul>
<li>Only use the horn when its absolutely necessary. Sometimes its prohibited to use it on some areas.</li>
<li>Do not use the horn to vent out your frustration. An example of this is when bicycle riders or sidewalk vendors use the road as if they were riding a car. Just give the horn a light tap, and if the bicycle rider still doesn&rsquo;t move to the side simply go pass them if the situation allows.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Stay Cool</h3>

<ul>
<li>Be sure to keep your head cool at all times. You don&rsquo;t want your driving to be affected because of your frustration.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Parking</h3>

<ul>
<li>Be sure that you are only parking your car where it is allowed.</li>
<li>Completely stop the car with the foot brake before putting the car into park mode and pulling the hand brake.</li>
<li>Be sure to leave enough space to maneuver your car later on. You don&rsquo;t want to get to close to another car to avoid scratching it.</li>
<li>If the situation allows, use reverse mode when parking your car, this means that the tail of your car goes inside and the head is outside. This makes it easier for you to go out later on.</li>
</ul>


<p>That&rsquo;s it! I&rsquo;m still a beginner at this so I&rsquo;ll be adding more things to this blog post in future as I learn more things about driving. For now I&rsquo;m going to leave you with this saying:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Better late than dead.</p></blockquote></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
