<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: health | Wern Ancheta]]></title>
  <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/categories/health/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-04T20:50:53+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Wern Ancheta]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to stay healthy as a developer]]></title>
    <link href="http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2013/05/11/how-to-stay-healthy-as-a-developer/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-11T19:14:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://anchetawern.github.io/blog/2013/05/11/how-to-stay-healthy-as-a-developer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Developers are not really the healthiest group of people in the planet simply because our faces are just buried in front of the computer 8 hours a day (or even more) 7 days a week. Were just sitting all day thinking of how to solve a problem, which technique to implement, and writing code.</p>

<!--More-->


<p>Here are the things that I personally observe in order to stay healthy:</p>

<ul>
<li>Exercise</li>
<li>Eat healthy foods</li>
<li>Stand while working</li>
<li>Sleep well</li>
<li>Take breaks</li>
</ul>


<h3>Exercise</h3>

<p>Always try to get atleast an hour of exercise everyday. Doesn&rsquo;t matter which time you exercise(either morning or afternoon) or what type of exercise you do. What&rsquo;s important is that you enjoy exercising and don&rsquo;t think of anything else while doing it.
I personally like brisk walking, jogging and running. I live close to a spacious school ground and that&rsquo;s where I usually exercise so there&rsquo;s really no excuse in not exercising.</p>

<h3>Eat healthy foods</h3>

<p>Always try to eat fruits, vegetables and have soup for every meal.
Soup helps in making the food easier to digest.
You can also try to eat less meat since meat is harder to digest than vegetable.
If you&rsquo;re the carnivorous type then there&rsquo;s no excuse in drinking 8 &ndash; 10 glasses of water everyday. Actually you can drink more if you&rsquo;re sweating a lot when exercising. Water helps in digestion, combine it with fiber which you can get from <a href="http://www.doctoroz.com/videos/50-fiber-rich-foods">a whole bunch of fruits and vegetables</a> leads to a healthier stomach.</p>

<p>Also try chew the food well, eating a meal in 20 to 30 minutes is a good indication that you&rsquo;re chewing your food well. The stomach digests the food that we eat but digestion actually starts in the mouth when we chew our food.
This will lead to better digestion which leads to better stomach and colon health.</p>

<h3>Stand while working</h3>

<p>Try to get a standing desk. Sitting is not good especially if you don&rsquo;t take frequent breaks.
If you don&rsquo;t have the budget or you&rsquo;re earning for something else you can always try to look for an alternative standing desk. I personally use our chest and drawer as my standing desk simply because it matches my elbow height and I feel comfortable using it.</p>

<h3>Sleep well</h3>

<p>Always try to get atleast 7 &ndash; 8 hours of sleep each night.
This ensures that our mind is in its optimum state when we wake up.
Fresh, happy and ready to solve some problems.</p>

<h3>Take breaks</h3>

<p>Take breaks every 50 &ndash; 60 minutes. Stretch up and do a micro-exercise, its a good way to make sure that your blood is flowing properly. Venous diseases like hemorrhoids, deep vein thrombosis, and varicose veins are born from not moving too much and staying in just one position all day.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
